<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Tempora mutantur A treatise, theological, moral, and historical. Representing (as in a scene) the vicissitudes of humane things, with their causes and uses. Fitted for the establishing mans soul unchangeable in the faith, amidst the various changes of the world. By J.R. Master of Arts.</title>
            <author>Robinson, John, Preacher at East-Thorpe.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 152KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 54 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58112</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829974</idno>
  <idno type="VID">34421</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240876765</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing R32B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R218373</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829974</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99829974e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58112)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 34421)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2015:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Tempora mutantur A treatise, theological, moral, and historical. Representing (as in a scene) the vicissitudes of humane things, with their causes and uses. Fitted for the establishing mans soul unchangeable in the faith, amidst the various changes of the world. By J.R. Master of Arts.</title>
                  <author>Robinson, John, Preacher at East-Thorpe.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 98 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Tho. Rooks at the Lamb and Ink-bottle at the West end of S. Paul's near S. Austin's gate, where also is made and sold the best ink for deeds and records,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1664.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>J.R. = John Robinson.</note>
                  <note>Running title: The birth of a day, or, a treatise of vicissitude.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original at the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Christian literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:34421:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Tempora Mutantur.</hi> A TREATISE, Theological, Moral, and Historical.</p>
            <p>Representing (as in a Scene) the Vicissitudes of Humane things, with their Causes and Uses.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fitted for the establishing mans Soul unchangeable in the Faith, amidst the various Changes of the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> J. R. <hi>Master of Arts.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Isa. 21.11, 12.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>He calls to me out of <hi>Seir,</hi> Watchman, what of the night?</p>
               <p>The Watchman said, The morning cometh and also the night.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Rooks</hi> at the <hi>Lamb</hi> and <hi>Ink-bottle</hi> at the <hi>West</hi> end of S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s near S. <hi>Austin</hi>'s gate, <hi>Where also is made and sold the best Ink for Deeds and Records,</hi> 1664.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:34421:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:34421:2"/>
            <head>To the RIGHT WORSHIPFULL S<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>G. B. Knight.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the wheeling motions of our late <hi>changes</hi> I have still observ'd you to be <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo quadratus,</hi> one whose <hi>Basis</hi> hath been firmly grounded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Religious principles;</hi> and amidst the manifold Alterations of the World's Scene (on which you have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted the <hi>suffering</hi> part) most con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant unto the <hi>Truth;</hi> your Heaven-born Soul over-looking these subluna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb facs="tcp:34421:3"/> mutations with an eye of <hi>Faith</hi> fixt upon <hi>Eternity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having therefore compos'd this Treatise, <hi>[The birth of a Day]</hi> brought forth by the midwifery of some weeks studies, I no sooner thought of seeking a <hi>Patron</hi> for it, then of choosing <hi>Your self;</hi> whose <hi>Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> (I knew well) could fully at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test the <hi>Vicissitudes</hi> of all <hi>Humane things,</hi> and whose <hi>Judgement</hi> did clearly discern their severall <hi>Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses,</hi> as having already apply'd them home in their <hi>sacred Uses.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the rather, S<seg rend="sup">r</seg>, do I make bold here to inscribe <hi>Your name,</hi> that I may erect, if but a <hi>small Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:34421:3"/> of <hi>Thankfulnesse</hi> unto you for sundry <hi>Favours;</hi> and let you see that I eye not <hi>Greatnesse</hi> so much as <hi>Goodnesse</hi> for the fittest <hi>Patron.</hi> The former of these having much of <hi>Vicissitude</hi> in it, being <hi>Aurâ fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacior,</hi> more fleeting then the <hi>Air;</hi> but the later of duration, being <hi>Aere perennior,</hi> more durable then <hi>Brass.</hi> And a greater testimony of this <hi>Goodnesse</hi> cannot be given, then your eminent and cheerfull <hi>suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> even the losse of <hi>All,</hi> your <hi>Constancy</hi> excepted in the <hi>Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox Faith,</hi> which hath taught you to look beyond the <hi>Instruments,</hi> unto <hi>God</hi> the <hi>principall Agent,</hi> in his so
<pb facs="tcp:34421:4"/> various and changeable dealings with you, as to earthly things.</p>
            <p>May these Lines then stand you in any stead, though to be only (as <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Hur</hi> were to <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses</hi>) some stay and support to your <hi>weak hands</hi> and <hi>feeble knees,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 17.12.</note> it is enough.</p>
            <p>For God who is rich in <hi>mercy</hi> to those that call upon him, hath a <hi>Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficit</hi> for <hi>You</hi> and <hi>Yours,</hi> and will at length make up all your <hi>losses</hi> (if you <hi>faint</hi> not under them) out of his own choicest <hi>treasure</hi> of <hi>happinesse,</hi> which no <hi>son of violence</hi> shall be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to force from You; since you have suffer'd as a <hi>Christian</hi> with undaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:34421:4"/>
               <hi>Fortitude</hi> and <hi>Patience,</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in your self that you have in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven a <hi>better</hi> and an <hi>enduring Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, Sir, I commend your <hi>VVorthy self</hi> with your <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Lady,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 20.32.</note> and your <hi>hopefull</hi> (as well as <hi>numerous) branch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es,</hi> unto <hi>God</hi> and the word of his <hi>Grace:</hi> nothing doubting but that He, who by the hand of his provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence hath the <hi>turning</hi> about of this great <hi>Globe</hi> of the <hi>World,</hi> will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in his good time, <hi>turn</hi> all to his <hi>Churches good:</hi> and as he is <hi>able</hi> every day to build you up more and more in your <hi>Holy Faith;</hi> so
<pb facs="tcp:34421:5"/> likewise he <hi>will</hi> do it, and give You an <hi>abiding inheritance</hi> among them that are <hi>sanctified.</hi> Which is the <hi>prayer</hi> of him who esteems it an <hi>Honour</hi> to be,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your faithfully devoted servant,</hi> John Robinson.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:34421:5"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PROV. 27. ver. 1. and last branch of it.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>For thou know'st not what a <hi>Day</hi> may bring forth.</p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>The whole Verse runs thus;</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Boast not of to Morrow; for thou know'st not what a <hi>Day</hi> may bring forth.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His verse is one of <hi>Solomons</hi> Proverbs spoken of 1 <hi>Reg.</hi> 4.32. where we read that <hi>Solomon spake three thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand Proverbs, and his Songs were a thousand and five.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now a Proverb is a speech of an Absolute and Independent nature. For which cause I shall not look back upon it as any ways Relative, but as standing by it self upon its own account.</p>
            <p>And in this Proverb two generall things are considerable.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A Prohibition, <hi>Boast not of to morrow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. A Reason of it, <hi>For thou knowest not, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in the Reason there are three Particulars observable.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Birth: And this is implied in the rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive <hi>Quid,</hi> which hath alwayes an <hi>Aliquid</hi> it relates unto, <hi>viz.</hi> some good or evil to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver'd of.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Parent that brings it forth: And this is <hi>A Day,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Veritas temporis filia, Aul. Gell. Noct. Attic. lib. <hi>12.</hi> cap. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> or every particular day. For as Truth is the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Time; so also is Falshood. It is Time that brings forth
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:34421:6"/> Births that are diversly shapen, both good and evill, strait and crooked, beautifull and defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, perfectly membred and monstrous. Our <hi>Gazetts</hi> and <hi>Diurnals</hi> can satisfie us thus far.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Persons that do ignorantly gaze after the Birth: And they are every man, <hi>Tu homo.</hi> And if it be ask'd then Who doth know it; it is answered, Only <hi>tu Domine.</hi> For <hi>secret things belong to the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 28.28.</note> sayes <hi>Moses:</hi> And fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture things are those secrets that God hath kept lock'd up from us in his own Bosome; He only knowing them <hi>a parte ante,</hi> we but <hi>a parte post.</hi> For as <hi>Bildad</hi> says,<note place="margin">Job. 8.9.</note> so may we, <hi>Hesterni sumus,</hi> That <hi>we are but Yesterdayes off-spring and know nothing,</hi> no, not so much as the issue of one Day, what it will produce. <hi>Thou Know'st not what a Day may bring forth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here I shall begin with the last of the three, viz. The persons that do ignorantly gaze after the Birth; And they are Every man; <hi>Tu homo.</hi> And the rather because it is first in the Text, and comprehensive of the rest. The sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance whereof I shall hold out unto you in two Propositions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That no man can tell the Future Event of things, no not for a day: and this comes to passe from the great vicissitude and unconstancy of all world<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y things. Or else, if I may but take in this Reason into the Proposition, then I shall run it thus;</p>
            <p>That there is such a Vicissitude and Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stancy in all Sublunary things, as that a man can have no assurance of them, no not for a day. We know not what a Day may bring forth.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:34421:6"/>
            <p>For in the great House of the World there be three Roomes; whereof the upper and lower have no change, nor shadow of change, the one being full of eternall Glory, the other of Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; only this middle-most is fill'd with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Instability.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That it is God alone knows all future things. For this word <hi>Thou</hi> is here put <hi>signan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> with an <hi>Emphasis</hi> upon it: <hi>Thou know'st not.</hi> As if he had said, Though the Knowledge of all Contingencies be hid from Man, yet are they known to God as if they were present. For which cause God hath his Name from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, <hi>I am that I am;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 3.14.</note> there being with him neither time past, nor time to come, but all being present.</p>
            <p>First then for the former of the two.</p>
            <p>Now for the orderly handling of this, that I may give some stays and rests to your memories, I shall lay before you these five things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. What this Vicissitude is.</item>
               <item>2. That there is such a Vicissitude.</item>
               <item>3. The Efficient Causes of it.</item>
               <item>4. The Ends or Final Causes of it.</item>
               <item>5. The Uses of it.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The first thing then is, <hi>Quid sit.</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
            </p>
            <p>Where know that by Vicissitude here I do not understand such a mutation as is the utter anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hilation of the Creatures Essence and Being; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause God having made all things, doth not ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly destroy any thing that he hath made, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that of S. <hi>Paul</hi> 1 Cor. 7.31. <hi>The fashion of the world passes away, (fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gura mundi, non natura,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aretius</hi> in locum.</note> as <hi>Aretius</hi> glosses it;) But such a one as doth
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:34421:7"/> only alter it in its present estate and condition; this particular estate and condition of a thing being the proper object of Vicissitude. Neither is it again every mutation of a things particular estate and condition that is the proper object of Vicissitude, but only such a mutation as is reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procall: <hi>i. e.</hi> such a change, as hath like the Sea its <hi>Fluxus</hi> and <hi>Refluxus,</hi> its Ebbings and Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings from one estate to another. And this too we do not understand in a Morall, but in a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall way. For there may be a Morall change from good to evil, and back again from evil to good, which yet we cannot call by the name of Vicissitude. But the Vicissitude here spoken of is only in Naturall and Worldly things, which have such a circular motion here, and are so un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>constant in it, as that there can be no Insurance made of them in this great Exchange of the World, because we know not concerning them what a day may bring forth. And so much for the first thing.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The second is the Demonstration of this Truth, That there is such a Vicissitude.</p>
            <p>And this I shall do, First, by expresse places of Scripture. Secondly, by some Instances of it.</p>
            <p>First, by some expresse places of Scripture. And here the Preacher hath a good saying, <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siastes</hi> 7.14. <hi>In the day of Prosperity be joyfull, but in the day of Adversity consider.</hi> And the thing we are to consider of is, <hi>That God hath set the one over against the other.</hi> His meaning is, That God hath ordered things here with a great deal of change and variety; As that he hath set Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sperity over against Adversity, and again, Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versity over against Prosperity, even as Light
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:34421:7"/> and Darknesse, to succeed each other by a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant intercourse: <hi>To the end,</hi> says he, <hi>That man should find nothing after him:</hi> i. e. that so by this interchangeable dealing of God, no man should be able to find out infallibly what his after e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state shall be in this world, whether happy or else miserable. Again consult that of S. <hi>Paul</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.31.<note place="margin">Videtur hic allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisse ad Scenas, in quibus aulaea momento compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cata novam red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunt faciem. <hi>Calvin.</hi> in locum.</note> where the world and all things in it are compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to a Scene in a Comedy, which being changed on the suddain, some new matter is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently presented to the eyes of the Spectatours. And S.<note place="margin">Nemo est Qui Deum credat sibi tam faven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinum ut possit sibi polliceri. Sen. Thy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est. trag. 3.</note>
               <hi>James</hi> again to the same purpose <hi>cap.</hi> 4. <hi>vers.</hi> 13. &amp; 14. <hi>Go to,</hi> &amp;c. The speech is Ironicall, as deriding those who think all things here below to be of a standing nature: when as the wheel of all sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunary things is so turning, that a man cannot tell what turn shall be on the morrow. That as the Scripture sayes of<note n="*" place="margin">Isa. 22.18.</note>
               <hi>Shebna,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Huic affine est il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lud Plautinum, Enim vero, dii nos quasi pilas, homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes habēt. Plaut. in Capt. Scen. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> That God should turn and tosse him like a Ball: so are all out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things turn'd and toss'd up and down by the Racket of Gods Power, and Providence, even as a man rackets a ball to &amp; fro from one place to another.</p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">O si possemus in talem ascendere speculam, ut to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Orbis osten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derem ruinas. Hieron. l. <hi>2.</hi> ad Heliod.</note> I shall demonstrate this by severall instances. And here methinks I could wish with S. <hi>Jerom,</hi> that I were now in the top of such a Watch-tower, that I might discover unto you the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ines and alterations of all things
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:34421:8"/> in the world, from the beginning of the Creation to this day; and present this lively to your eyes, which I am fain to do now only to your minds and understandings; that so I might be able to say with the prophet <hi>David,</hi> Psal. 46.8. <hi>Come and behold the works of the Lord, what desola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> so what changes and alterations, <hi>he hath wrought in the world!</hi> For <hi>one generation,</hi> says the Preacher,<note place="margin">Ecclesiast. 1.4.</note>
               <hi>is passing away, and another comes:</hi> neither is there any thing here so fix'd, that it can say of it self as the false Prophets did,<note place="margin">Isa. 56. last. Sic vulg. Latin.</note>
               <hi>Erit sicut hodie, sic &amp; cras, To morrow shall be with me as this day;</hi> Since no man knows what a day may bring forth. Now this I shall hold out unto you in a threefold respect, that ye may be the more affected with it.</p>
            <p>First, in relation to Politick Estates and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments.</p>
            <p>Secondly, to continued Families, or Races of men that are lineally successive for Name and Greatnesse.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, to particular Persons.</p>
            <p>In all which if I be more historicall then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise I would, it must be imputed to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Subject, which is of that nature, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires it of me.</p>
            <p>First then I shall consider it in relation to Politick Estates and Governments: whether we consider them either as drawn out in length in Monarchies; or else as drawn up short in Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which are nothing else but Empires epito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mized, or Republicks bound up in a lesser vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Lib. 4. de rep. c. 1.</note>First then I shall demonstrate this unto you in Monarchies, which <hi>Bodine</hi> tells us are more du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:34421:8"/> then Popular States, because lesse sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to be divided, (Unity being the great Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>server of all things:) and yet have these had,<note place="margin">Dies, hora, momentum e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertendis dominationibus sufficit, quae adamanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis credebantur radicibus esse fundatae. <hi>Sir Walt. Rawl. preface out of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saub.</hi>
               </note> as the Moon, not only their increase and full light, but also their wain and changes, and this sometimes in a moment. That as in Musick you shall hear sometimes a string tun'd up to its <hi>ultimum potentiae,</hi> as high as it will bear, and presently depressed again to the lowest Key, and another elevated, yet both of them breathing but light aires and of short continuance: So may you see a Monarchy now wound up to the highest pitch of Happiness, and by and by let down a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain into the lowest depths of misery.<note place="margin">Regnorum initia, incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meneum &amp; occasus à De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent. <hi>Phil. de Commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes lib. 7.</hi>
               </note> This is the Lords doing, and it is marvellous in our eyes.</p>
            <p>And here I shall begin with those Empires and Monarchies that were most famous among the rest.</p>
            <p>For how soon was the <hi>Assyrian</hi> or <hi>Babylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> Monarchy swallow'd up by the <hi>Persian,</hi> the <hi>Persian</hi> by the <hi>Greek</hi> or <hi>Macedonian</hi> Empire, and the <hi>Greek</hi> by the <hi>Roman?</hi> which the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Daniel</hi> presents unto us by the Gold, Silver, Brasse and Iron whereof <hi>Nebuchadnezzars</hi> I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage consisted, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.32. The dissolution of one, as in naturall things, so here, being still the generation of another; and again the erection of the later being the destruction of the former.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:34421:9"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">I. Flor. <hi>in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditu ad</hi> hist.</note>And as for the <hi>Romane</hi> Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, their own Historian can tell us of that, how it had both its Infancy,<note place="margin">Imperiorum nunc floret for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuna, nunc se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nescit, nunc in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terit, <hi>Patere. hist. lib. 2.</hi>
               </note> Youth, Manhood, and Old age as it were by turnes. As its Infancy under Kings, its Youth under Consuls, its Manhood from the first <hi>Punick</hi> warre unto the time of <hi>Augustus Caesar,</hi> and from that time its Old age under the succeeding Emperours; untill at length that solid Body was torn asunder by the struglings of her own Children, into the Eastern and Western Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires, whereof the former was soon eaten out by the <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Saracens,</hi> and the later also fell away much after a little revolution of time, by the falling off of divers Nations from her, each of which after they had pluck'd off their own feathers from the <hi>Roman</hi> Eagle, left her al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most naked; As the <hi>Franks</hi> and <hi>Burgundians</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> the <hi>Goths</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> the <hi>Normans</hi> and <hi>Lombards</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> together with the <hi>English</hi> and <hi>Scots</hi> in <hi>Britain:</hi> untill at the last cast the <hi>Roman</hi> Monarchy began a little to recall her self into <hi>Germany,</hi> where she hath held up since little more then the bare name of the Empire. So that Vicissitude you see is the great Empresse of the world, unto whose unstay'd dominion all earthly Powers and Principalities must be sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, even those that are of the first Magnitude, much more others that move in a lower Orbe.</p>
            <p>And of these I shall single out only three, which I conceive most eminent, to be instanced in for this point.</p>
            <p>The first is <hi>Judea,</hi> whose government was
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:34421:9"/> Monarchically settled by God himself;<note place="margin">See 1 Sam. cap. 10.</note> yet how oft did she change her Lords and Masters, yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her self as it were successively first to the <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylonian,</hi> and after that to the <hi>Roman, Persian, Saracen, Christian, Aegyptian,</hi> and now to the <hi>Turkish</hi> power? That as the<note n="*" place="margin">Ovid.</note> Poet spake of <hi>Troy, fuit Ilium;</hi> so may we of <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> her <hi>Metropolis, fuit Hierosolyma,</hi> that <hi>Jerusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> was, She <hi>was great among the Nations,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lam. 1.1.</note> or <hi>Domina Gentium, the Lady of the Nations,</hi> as the Vulgar <hi>Latin</hi> reads it. But now, <hi>Non sic ut olim,</hi> It hath not been with her for these many generations past <hi>as in former days,</hi> (to use <hi>Job's</hi> words in his twenty ninth chapter, second and third verses) <hi>when God preserv'd her, when his Candle shined upon her head, and when by that light she walk'd through darknesse;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lam. 5.8.</note> but <hi>Servants have ruled over her, and there was none to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver her out of their hands.</hi> Which is a good le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of Mutability to other Kingdomes and their Mother-cities. For <hi>Jerusalem</hi> was once a holy and happy city, and had been happy still, had she but continued holy; but that failing,<note place="margin">Lam. 4.1.</note>
               <hi>How is her Gold become dimme, how is her fine Gold chang'd into Drosse!</hi> as she complains her self.</p>
            <p>The second Example I produce here is <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>As</hi> Pertinax <hi>the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour was call'd</hi> Pila For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunae; Nam quod Ethni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci Fortunam, nos Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ani providentiam appella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus. <hi>Aurel. Vict. Epitom.</hi>
               </note> which we may well call the Ball of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence: And indeed so it was, being bandyed from one Lord to another ten severall times, before it came to lie (as now it doth) at the foot of <hi>Spain.</hi> For being a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey at first diversly peopled, it was upon the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vision
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:34421:10"/> allotted to the Eastern Emperours, but from them forc'd by the <hi>Almains,</hi> and so to the <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Saracens,</hi> and then successively hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried about to the <hi>Normans, Germans, Frenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Hungarians, Arragonoys,</hi> and from them to the <hi>French</hi> again; till in the end the <hi>Spaniard</hi> seised upon it: and whether it will continue long with him or no, is very uncertain; especially if we remember how of late years a poor Fisherman,<note place="margin">See <hi>Howels</hi> rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it lately printed.</note> (<hi>Massinello</hi> by name) snatch'd up the reines of Government from; him &amp; (had not God otherwise determined of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome by infatuating that Mushrome King) for ought we know, he might have runne quite a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with them, so slippery are all earthly King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes!</p>
            <p n="3">3. But not to look out any longer to other nations of <hi>Christendome,</hi> (methinks) we may instance this best by reflecting upon our selves. For you all know (I suppose) how the <hi>Romans, Saxons, Danes</hi> and <hi>Normans</hi> had each of them their severall and alternate dayes of Lordship over this Nation; but yet because they did not know in those their days the things that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long'd unto their Peace, how do we see the sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows of the night stretched out upon them, their Suns set with us, and their days shut in!</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Josh. 10.13.</note>The longest day we read of was that in <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suah's</hi> time, wherein though the Sun stood still in <hi>Gibeon</hi> for the space of a whole day, yet set it did at last.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">See our <hi>Engl. Chronicle.</hi>
               </note>The day of the <hi>Romans</hi> was long upon our Horizon, for the Sun of their prosperity shone
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:34421:10"/> here for the space of four hundred years and more; Yet did it then go down as to us in this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Darknesse here now doth lie upon it.</p>
            <p>Again, the day of the <hi>Saxons</hi> continued five hundred years and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards;<note n="*" place="margin">So long they tyranni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed here, but reign'd only twenty six under <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute, Harold</hi> and <hi>Hardie Canute.</hi>
               </note> That of the <hi>Danes</hi> two hundred fifty five years or thereabouts.</p>
            <p>And how long the day of the <hi>Normans</hi> hath lasted every petty Almanack can tell us. I, and if none of those Suns come to rise again within our Hemisphere (when the sins of this Nation are ripe, and call for Gods sickle to cut them down) its beside his ordinary rule, which usually runs out all humane things by a changeable cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference; for so <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us in his book of <hi>Ecclesiastes, That the Sun rises,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chap. 1. vers. 5.</note>
               <hi>and the Sun goes down, &amp; hasteth to the place where he arose.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither is this all, that the Powers and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities on earth are upon a daily turn, but as the <hi>Primum Mobile</hi> (you know) carries about the other Spheres; so do these carry about many other changes and alterations with them: As that of Religion, Laws, Liberties, Sciences, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stoms and such like. Nay, even the Houses of God, which before to violate was held a crime inexpiable, yet are they now upon such removes broken down without scruple;<note place="margin">The heathen therefore did superscribe their Urns thus, <hi>Diis munibus Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crum:</hi> And the Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans set <hi>Deo Opt. Max. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crum</hi> upon their Tombes and Gravestones.</note> and the very Urns of the Dead, which have been alwayes look'd upon as sacred Cabinets to preserve the bodies of Gods Saints in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:34421:11"/> for Eternity, yet are they now broken up, and their Ashes thrown about (such is the unsetled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of all things here below) even as the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lest Dust upon the face of the earth.</p>
            <p>Beloved, it hath been ever thus upon the conversion of such great bodies,<note place="margin">Res Deus no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stras celeri cita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas turbine ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>savit. <hi>Sen. in Thyest.</hi>
               </note> and it is so still: For never was there any conversion in this Land like to that our eyes have seen of late; That if any one should have slept but some few years last past (as the Ancients fain of <hi>Epimenides</hi>) and should have awaked again in these times,<note place="margin">Quinquaginta annos dormiisse fingitur.</note> how would he wonder at those strange <hi>Metamorphoses</hi> that are now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, there being <hi>Nova rerum facies,</hi> A new face of things both in Church and State!<note place="margin">I heard M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                  <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> say. He sought for <hi>Rome</hi> in <hi>Rome</hi> and could not find her. <hi>Juel</hi> in his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pology, 2. part, divis. 21.</note> Insomuch (as M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Harding</hi> spake some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times of <hi>Rome,</hi> That he did <hi>quaerere Romam in Roma,</hi> That he did seek <hi>Rome</hi> in <hi>Rome,</hi> and could not find it,) so may we say now, That we may <hi>quaerere Angliam in Anglia,</hi> That we may now seek for old <hi>England</hi> in our new <hi>England,</hi> and yet go without it, it is so much chang'd from what it was before.</p>
            <p>And as we have seen much of this already, so who knows but we may come to see a great deal more hereafter? Since we know not what a Day may bring forth.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Neither is this true only in Empires and Monarchies, but also in Cities and their
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:34421:11"/> popular Governments. <hi>Etiam summis negatum est urbibus stare diu,</hi> says the Moralist.<note place="margin">Seneca.</note> And to this purpose tends that of the Authour to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> Heb. 13.14.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cain</hi> therefore sayes Saint <hi>Augustine,</hi> built a city, but <hi>Abel</hi> none. <hi>Civitas e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim Sanctorum superna.</hi> Lib. 15. <hi>de Civit. Dei</hi> cap. 1.</note>
               <hi>We have here no abiding city, but we look for one to come, whose founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is in the heavens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is then no City on earth, nor any kind of Government in it that ever stood up long in one posture, none that ever was, or shall be abiding. <hi>Passe ye up to</hi> Calneh <hi>and see,</hi> saies the Prophet, <hi>Amos</hi> 6.2. <hi>and from hence go to</hi> Hemath <hi>the Great, and so to</hi> Gath <hi>of the</hi> Philistins. So passe ye up to <hi>Athens,</hi> the eye of <hi>Greece</hi> for Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and humane Literature, and see, and from thence go to <hi>Rome,</hi> the head of the Western Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, and so come to <hi>Florence,</hi> the beauty of <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taly;</hi> (for I forbear to name more, Examples in this kinde being almost infinite) in all which you may read this truth at large.</p>
            <p>And first for <hi>Athens:</hi> How many changes of Governours and Governments did she endure? putting her self off from hereditary Kings to Archons, or Aristocraticall Lords, who govern'd first for terme of life, then decennially, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter these to Democraticall Rulers.</p>
            <p>Next for <hi>Rome;</hi>
               <note place="margin">By <hi>Brennus</hi> King of the <hi>Gauls</hi> Anno Mundi <hi>3562;</hi> By <hi>Alaricus</hi> King of the <hi>Goths</hi> An. Christ. <hi>410.</hi> By <hi>Gensericus</hi> King of the <hi>Vandals 447.</hi> &amp;c. and by the Duke of <hi>Burbon</hi> An. <hi>1527.</hi> vide plura in <hi>Bucholcer.</hi> chronol.</note> how oft hath that city been alter'd by <hi>Gauls, Hunnes, Goths</hi> and <hi>Vandals?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea how oft hath the Government of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:34421:12"/> it been pass'd away from one hand to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>It is mystically represented to us <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.3. by the Beast of seven heads, which is there in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted by the seven Hills it is built upon,<note place="margin">Idèo dicta est <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma</hi> urbs Septicollis, <hi>Godwin Antiq.</hi> lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> to be <hi>Rome:</hi> And according to the number of those Hills, to so many ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters did it submit it self, who had their severall turnes of su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme power and regiment o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver her;<note place="margin">Vide <hi>Tacit.</hi> ad initium hist.</note> as <hi>Kings, Consuls, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctators, Decemviri, Tribunes, Emperous</hi> and <hi>Popes:</hi> under the last of which I do not find that it was ever besieged by any that took it not;<note place="margin">Downh. <hi>de</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tich. <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 4.</note> such strange ebbings hath that Sea had experience of!</p>
            <p>Last of all for <hi>Florence.</hi> It is strange to tell what various whirlings about that hath had in point of supreme rule and power. For at first the Nobility ruled it in an Aristocraticall way. B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t a little after some Grandees among the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple wrested it to themselves: who being tired out with continuall quarrellings one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, (for the people were divided into three ranks) the middle sort of them took upon them the management of the State. And these also falling quickly together by the eares, the third and lowest sort became masters of it. Which holding not long by reason of their mutuall dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords, they yield themselves and the government of their City unto <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>France,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vide <hi>Machiavils</hi> Hist. of <hi>Florence.</hi>
               </note> brother to <hi>Lewis</hi> the ninth;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:34421:12"/> who within a short time being invited to the Kingdome of <hi>Naples,</hi> and leaving only Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties at <hi>Florence,</hi> the <hi>Florentines</hi> return to their Popular Government, and renew their civill warres among themselves. For redresse whereof they send for the Duke of <hi>Athens,</hi> and give up all to him. But shortly they supposing themselves to be brought in bondage, and to be despoiled of their liberty by the fear of his guard, banish him the City, and within lesse then one years space shake off his government over them. After which they come to an Aristocracie again, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vising new Names and Officers for their Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates, and changing and rechanging them so oft, that sometimes their State was no better or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd then if it had been committed to mad men or children without discretion, the city scarce twenty yeares together keeping the same forme of State: but as sick men in fevers (says<note n="*" place="margin">Lib. 4. de Rep. cap. 1.</note>
               <hi>Bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi>) desire to be remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved now hither,<note place="margin">Quid refert quod alibi fuerit aeger, cum non ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, locumve mutârit, cum non exuat aegritudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem? <hi>Lipsius de Const.</hi> Quocunque aegrum trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuleris, secum morbum transferet. <hi>Sen. Epist. 17.</hi>
               </note> and by and by thither, or from one bed to another, as if the disease were in the places where they lay, and not in the intralls of their own bodies; so were the <hi>Florentines</hi> still turning their State, till they turnd it into the hands of the <hi>Medices,</hi> who now hold it. A thing almost incredible (says he) did not their own Recorder leave it recorded to posterity.</p>
            <p>But in the second place let us descend to Families or Races of men that are li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neally
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:34421:13"/> successive for Name and Greatnesse.</p>
            <p>And here let me ask, where are those Illustri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Families cried up so much in former times, and famous in their generations?</p>
            <p>As the Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the <hi>Mac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabees</hi> in <hi>Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eight <hi>Maccabean</hi> Princes and Kings swayd the sceptre of <hi>Jewry</hi> one after another: So also did eleven <hi>Ptolemies</hi> in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> till the <hi>Romans</hi> made themselves heires to it.</note> and of the <hi>Ptolemies</hi> in <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The <hi>Zelzuccian</hi> Line or Family gave way to the <hi>Oguzian</hi> or <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>toman</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat now reigns: So did the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laeologi</hi> after seven successions.</note>Again, where is the <hi>Zelzuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian</hi> Family in the lesser <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sia,</hi> and the Imperiall Family of the <hi>Palaeologi</hi> in <hi>Greece?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">There were <hi>21</hi> Kings of this line in <hi>France</hi> one after another descended from <hi>Meroveu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>;</hi> These yielded to <hi>Pip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pin</hi> the first of the second race, whose line ended in <hi>Ludovicus</hi> the fifth, and then came in the <hi>Capets,</hi> the present King being the thirtieth from <hi>Hugh Capet,</hi> and of the <hi>French</hi> bloud.</note>That of the <hi>Merovignians</hi> in <hi>France?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of the <hi>Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagenets</hi> in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Name and Glory of the <hi>Planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genets</hi> was swallow'd up of the <hi>Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors</hi> in <hi>Henry</hi> the seventh, who mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried <hi>Elizabeth</hi> the Heir of the <hi>York<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ish</hi> House. <hi>Heil. Geogr.</hi>
               </note> with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more of this rank I might name, did not the narow com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passe of so small a Treatise bound me?</p>
            <p>Tell me, is not the Name and Greatnesse of these Families long since expired, the Roots and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:34421:13"/> Branches of them quite remov'd, and others planted in their roomes? Examples of this sort are innumerable, as <hi>Elihu</hi> saies in <hi>Job:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 34.24.</note>
               <hi>He breaks in pieces mighty men without number;</hi> (so mighty Families without number) <hi>and sets up others in their stead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as for such Families as are of a lower forme, we need not go farre, since our own knowledge here will lead us to continuall chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and alterations,</p>
            <p>For thou hast seen it may be many Families heretofore in this Nation, brim full of earthly happinesse, and running over; and now upon thy second view of them behold there is no such thing, but they are much alter'd, and running very low in the world, if not clean run out.</p>
            <p>So that prosperity (you see) was never yet so entail'd upon any Family, and the Heirs thereof, but within a little time some one or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath cut it off.</p>
            <p>But last of all, if we look upon particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar persons, this will appear most evident; but especially if we consider them three wayes. In respect of their Bodies, Minds, and Estates.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gregory Nazianzen</hi> hath an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent saying of the two former joyntly consider'd, which is this;<note place="margin">In his Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion de Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritu Sancto.</note>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>i. e.</hi> We are not mixt creatures only, but also contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry both to others and our selves: not continuing truly the same no not so much as one day; but both in regard of our bodies and minds
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:34421:14"/> perpetually flowing and perpetually changing.</p>
            <p>And we can instance this in all the stages of our life, wherein by the ordinary course of nature, we are first weak, and then strong, and after weak again. As in our Childhood we are then weak both in Body and Mind; in our Youth, strong in Body and weak in Mind; and in our Manhood strong in both; but in our Old age strong in Mind and weak in Body; and in our Decrepit,<note place="margin">Senes bis pueri.</note> weak again in both, as we were in our Childhood at the first.</p>
            <p>But to leave this generall consideration of them, and to look upon them now more distinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and severally by themselves. And first for the change of particular Persons in regard of their Bodies.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">In his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pist.</note>And here it is true of them what <hi>Seneca</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>no man is the same to day, he was yesterday: Ego ipse</hi> (says he) <hi>dum haec lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor mutari, mutatus sum.</hi> Our Bodies (says he) are like a River, which keeps nothing but the bare name that was first given it; for as touching the present individuall matter which is the watry substance of it, this is alwayes transient, and other comes into its room: And so it is with the Body of man, which is alwayes receiving in new air and life, and venting the former. Which makes <hi>David</hi> professe of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, that he was toss'd up and down like the lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cust; and <hi>Job</hi> compare man for his bodily sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance to a Flower that never continues in one stay, <hi>Job</hi> 14.2. For now we are strong, and by and by weak; now beautifull, and present<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deformed. A little Fit of the Feaver, Small Pox, or the like, alters us so, as if we were
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:34421:14"/> not the same men we were before; insomuch that we hear some speaking thus unto us,<note place="margin">Ovid.</note> — <hi>Heu quantum mutatus ab illo!</hi> Alas, how hath this fit alter'd you from what you were in your health! for how are your lips grown pallid, your cheeks discolour'd, your eyes sunck into their holes, and your face quite disfigur'd! And o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers there be of our acquaintance that like <hi>Jobs</hi> three friends do lift up their eyes afarre off,<note place="margin">Job 2.12.</note> and know us not; so much are we chang'd in respect of our Bodies!</p>
            <p>But secondly, Let us consider it also in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of mens minds.</p>
            <p>And here (to say nothing of a morall change,<note place="margin">Rebus cunctis inest qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam velut Orbis, ut quem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>admodum temporū vices, ita &amp; Morum vertan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur: <hi>Tacit. Annal. lib. 3.</hi>
               </note> which is obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous every where) as on the one side we find nothing more notable <hi>Quinquennio Neronis,</hi> then the first five years of <hi>Nero's</hi> Reigne, and more excellent then his Youth; Yet afterwads having well tasted the sweet morsell of Soveraignty,<note place="margin">Bodin. <hi>de rep.</hi> lib. 4. cap. 1.</note> he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came (says one) the most de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testable Tyrant that ever was: And so also of <hi>Herod</hi> the Great <hi>Philo</hi> says, that he reign'd six years as a good and just Prince, presenting the <hi>Protasis</hi> of his Reign with a large Fringe of Goodnesse about it; (as <hi>Joaz, Amazias,</hi> and <hi>Ozias</hi> did) but as for the <hi>Catastrophe</hi> of it, that was very sad and fearfull. So on the other side, we find <hi>Manas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seh</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> soaking the forepart of their lives in blood, being no better at first then
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:34421:15"/>
               <hi>Nero</hi> was at the last, even a piece of clay temper'd with bloud;<note place="margin">Lutum fanguine commixtum. <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eton.</hi> in vita.</note> yet was their end like the end of <hi>Davids</hi> good man, <hi>The end of that man is peace.</hi> Psal. 37.37.</p>
            <p>But to wave these, (whereof much might be said, did it not quite lye out of my road I am now in,) and to insist only upon the changea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blenesse that doth naturally adhere to the Mind of man.</p>
            <p>Now tell me, if any thing in the world may be said to be more moveable then the Mind of man.</p>
            <p>It is a spirituall substance, and so is alwayes moving (though insensibly) from one thing unto another, never resting, untill at last like <hi>Noah</hi>'s dove it be taken into the Heavenly Ark.<note place="margin">Talis est mens cum pennas acceperit. <hi>Homil. 22.</hi> ad <hi>Hebraeos.</hi>
               </note> S. <hi>Chrysostome</hi> therefore com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares it to a Bird which flies in a moment of time over mountains and hills, over seas and rocks, without any hindrance: for now it is upon the lowest Shrub, and presently upon the highest branch of the tallest Cedar; now upon heavenly, and within the twinkling of an eye upon earthly things; now at <hi>Dan,</hi> and in a trice at <hi>Beersheba;</hi> now at one part of the earth, and then at another; for sometimes it is soring after <hi>Principalities and Powers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 6.12.</note>
               <hi>and spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Wickednesses in high places,</hi> as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle speaks, then after Riches, and by and by after Pleasures; now rejoycing, and then sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing; now quieted, and immediately trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and as soon pacified again; now ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:34421:15"/> and straightway fearing those hopes; now loving, and then hating what it loved be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: <hi>Sic omnia mutabilitati subjacent</hi> (saies Saint <hi>Augustine.</hi>
               <note place="margin">In his se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquy.</note>) Thus do all things lie down under mutability! And it amazed Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> much to consider how in the same moment of time his mind was not only diversly,<note place="margin">Illud supra modum stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendum, quod sub eodem momento contrariis affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctibus distrahor; <hi>Bern.</hi> de inter. dom. <hi>c. 64.</hi> ubi plura.</note> but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise contrarily affected, and as it were pull'd a pieces betwixt love and hatred, joy and sorrow, fear and hope, having as many varieties of affections within him, as there were diversities of things in the world for them to light upon.</p>
            <p>So that you see how the severall Passions of our Minds do in a breath, and with the turning of a hand steere divers wayes, first looking one way and then another, according as they are wheeled about with the motions of outward Contingencies.</p>
            <p>But in the last place we shall adde unto the former the great changes that particular men are subject to in regard of their outward Estates and Fortunes.<note place="margin">Habet suas vices conditio mortalium, ut adversa ex secundis, ex adversis iti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem secunda nascantur, <hi>Plin. jun.</hi> in his Pane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyr. to <hi>Trajan.</hi>
               </note> For the condition of Mortals (says a heathen man) hath its turnes and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnes, both of Prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Adversity.</p>
            <p>That as in a military skirmish there be some come up to discharge, while others fall off: so is it in the World's <hi>Militia.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:34421:16"/>
            <p>One there is that is rais'd out of the Dust to sit among Princes: whereas there is another that is flung down from the pinnacle of worldly joy and prosperity, and stated, as <hi>Job</hi> was, upon the Dunghill.<note place="margin">Ecelesiast. cap. 4. ver. 14.</note> And this doth the Preacher tell us among the rest of those changes that fell under his observation, <hi>That one comes out of Prison to reign,</hi> (as Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> did out of the Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to the Throne) <hi>whereas also</hi> there is <hi>he that is born in his Kingdome</hi> and <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes</hi> very <hi>poor;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 110.</note> (as our <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the third was, while he lived somtimes on the Churches Alms.)</p>
            <p>God hath appointed us (saith one well) all our parts to play,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>S<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Walt. Rawl.</hi> in Praef. to bis hist. of the world.</note> and hath not in their distri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution been either spare-hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the meanest, nor yet partiall to the greatest.</p>
            <p>He gave <hi>Caius Marius</hi> at first the part of a Carpenters sonne, but afterwards the part of one that was seven times Consul. So also <hi>Agathocles</hi> the part of a Potters son at the first, but afterwards of the King of <hi>Sicily.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So also on the other side <hi>Darius</hi> playd the part one while of the greatest Emperour, and another time of the most miserable Beggar, beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging but a little water to quench the drought of Death. And <hi>Bajazet</hi> playd the Grand Signior in the morning, but in the evening stood for <hi>Tamerlains</hi> footstool.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Jane Shore, Edward</hi> the fourths Minion, acts now as Mistresse of a stately Pallace, and a little after dies in a ditch for want of a house;<note place="margin">Ovid. Epist.</note> and (as he said of <hi>Icarus</hi>) so may we of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:34421:16"/> her, that —<hi>Nomina fecit aquis,</hi> she gave name to the place where she died, it being call'd from her <hi>Shore-ditch</hi> to this day.</p>
            <p>But I forbear, since there is enough recorded for our use in the sacred Scriptures to this purpose; where we find an example of the one in <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 78.71.</note> who sayes that God <hi>took him from following the Ewes with young,</hi> and set him upon the Throne; there <hi>to feed</hi> (as he says) Jacob <hi>his people, and</hi> Israel <hi>his inheritance.</hi> And to go lower yet, not only from the sheepfold, so he says Psal. 113.7. and 8 verses; <hi>God takes the poor out of the Dust, and the needy out of the Dunghill: That he may set him among Princes, even with the Princes of his people.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sterquilinio ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectior. <hi>Erasm. Adag.</hi> pag. <hi>110.</hi>
               </note> Now more vile and contemptible then the Dust we tread upon, which the least breath of wind commands any way, or then the worst of dust which is that of the Dunghill, we cannot be; yet these are they (says the <hi>Psalmist</hi>) whom he sets among Princes, even with the Princes of his people.</p>
            <p>An example of the other we have in <hi>Antiochus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luxuriant animi re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus plerumque secun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis, <hi>Ovid.</hi> lib. <hi>2.</hi> de <hi>Art. Amandi.</hi>
               </note> 2 Mac. 9.9. who was so fill'd with Pride through the ranknesse of his Prosperity, that he thought he might command the Sea, (so proud was he, sayes the Text, beyond the condition of man) and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that he could weigh the Mountains in a ballance, and reach up to the starres of heaven: Yet by and by is his combe cut, all
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:34421:17"/> his Glory worm-eaten, and none able to endure him for the filthinesse of his smell.</p>
            <p>Adde to this the example of <hi>Balthazar,</hi> Dan. 5.5. who was now carousing in the consecrated Vessels that <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> his Grandfather had plundred the Temple of and House of God at <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> as you may see 2 <hi>Kings</hi> chap. last. But in the same hour (saies the Text) came out the hand-writing of the wall against him, and then was the Kings countenance chang'd, his thoughts troubled, the joints of his loynes loos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and his Kingdome given away to the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Persians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus are we for outward things like so many Counters, which stand one while for a pound, and another for a penny.</p>
            <p>That as we see commonly in High-wayes, where one man hath set his foot, another pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently follows him and treads it out again; so is it usually, That if one man beat out an Honour or Estate to himself,<note place="margin">Nunc ager Umbreni sub nomine, nuper O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felli Dictus, sed nulli pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prius— <hi>Horat. serm.</hi> lib. <hi>2.</hi> Satyr. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> another comes after and treads out that impression, and whose it shall be next there is no man knows. Nay <hi>Lucan, Ipsa vices natura subit—</hi> Even the whole course of nature runs about in a circular motion; Our Bodies, Minds, and outward felicities, whatsoever we are, or what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever we have, are all subject to change in such wise, that we can have no assurance of them, no not for a day. We know not what a Day may bring forth.</p>
            <p>And so much for the demonstration of this
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:34421:17"/> truth, <hi>viz.</hi> That there is such a Vicissitude.</p>
            <p>The next thing is the Efficient Causes of it. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> For we never know any thing throughly,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Scire est per causam scire,</hi> Arist. phys. 2. cap. 3.</note> (says the Philosopher) untill we know the Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of it.</p>
            <p>Now in speaking to this, I shall proceed fiirst, negatively; secondly, affirmatively.</p>
            <p>First, Negatively, in shewing what have been thought to be the causes of all Changes and Alterations, yet are not so indeed. And here the <hi>Epicures</hi> and vulgar Heathen have thought <hi>Fortune</hi> to be the cause of them;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sors omnia versat,</hi> Virgil. Bucolic. Eg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log. 9.</note> And they define it thus, to be <hi>An Event of things without Reason.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But how unreason<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able it is to say that an Event of things without a Cause,<note place="margin">Si eventum nulla causa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum connexione productū, casum esse definias, nihil omnino casū esse confirmo. <hi>Boët. de consol. philos.</hi> l. <hi>5.</hi> pros. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> should be the Cause of all Events, judge ye.</p>
            <p>For it was only the ignorance of the true Causes that made the name of <hi>Fortune;</hi> there being nothing fortuitous in it self, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to us and our ignorance; since the power and providence of God hath the ordering and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing of all things here below. And this did the wiser sort among them confesse, as the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrist tells us.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Nullum numen abest si sit prudentia,<note place="margin">Juvenal. Satyr. 10.</note> sed te</l>
               <l>Nos facimus Fortuna Deam—</l>
            </q>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:34421:18"/>
            <p>Others again, as the <hi>Stoicks,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Regitur fatis mortale ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, nec sibi quisquam spondere potest firmum ac stabile. <hi>Sen. trag. Octav.</hi> Non illa Deo vertisse li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet quae nexa suis currunt causis. <hi>Sen.</hi> in <hi>OEdip.</hi> Fatum <hi>Stoicum</hi> definit <hi>Senec.</hi> Necessitatem rerum omnium Deum ipsum &amp; actiones omnes huic fato subjicientem. vid. <hi>Lips.</hi> lib. <hi>1.</hi> de Const. cap. <hi>17. 18.</hi>
               </note> make <hi>Fate</hi> or <hi>Destiny</hi> the cause of all Alterations, which they say is An Event that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarily falls out from a certain inevitable or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and connection of naturall Causes, work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing without the will of God, as the supreme Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer and Disposer of them, he being subjected to them, and not they to him: whereby they take away the very na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Godhead, which is to be a most powerfull and free Agent, that works what, and by what means it pleases; all seconda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry causes depending upon that, and that upon none.</p>
            <p>But enough of these; For I must remember my self, that I am now speaking to <hi>Christians,</hi> who acknowledge the Divine Providence in all things; and therefore shall speak no more of these Negative and supposed Causes, but shall now give you the true Efficient Causes of them by way of Affirmation.</p>
            <p>And here know that <hi>Logicians</hi> tell us of two Efficient Causes; Principall, and lesse Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall: And this is twofold, Impulsive and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strumentall.</p>
            <p>First then, the Principall Cause of all Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and Alterations is God; for so said the Heathen man,<note place="margin">Horat. Carm. l. 1. Ode 34.</note>
               <q>
                  <l>—Valet ima summis</l>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:34421:18"/>
                  <l>Mutare, &amp; insignem attenuat Deus,</l>
                  <l>Obscura promens—</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>But why borrow I weapons from the <hi>Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stins</hi> forge, when as there is enough for this that may be drawn out of Gods Armory of the Scriptures? as <hi>Psal.</hi> 75. the 6. and 7. verses: <hi>Promotion,</hi> saies the Prophet, <hi>comes neither from the East, nor from the West, nor from the South; but God is the Judge, he puts down one, and sets up another.</hi> So also <hi>Job</hi> 34. vers. 29. <hi>When he gives Quietnesse, who can make Trouble?</hi> and <hi>when he hides his face, who can behold him; whether it be done</hi> (saies <hi>Elihu) against a nation, or against a particular man only?</hi> Again <hi>Amos</hi> 5.8. <hi>He makes the Seven Starres and</hi> Orion, <hi>and turnes the shadow of Death into the morning: The Lord is his Name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Oratour expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses this well,<note place="margin">Ut hominum membra nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la contentione mente ipsa ac voluntate moventur: Sic divino numine moven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ac mutantur omnia, <hi>Tully</hi> lib. <hi>5.</hi> de natura Deorum.</note> by compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Gods omnipotency to the power of the soul over the members of the body, which upon the least intimation of the mind do turn and move about with all facility. Now God (saies he) is the sole mind of the Universe, and hath all parts and parcells there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of at his beck and pleasure, to be turn'd into a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny shape or form at his disposall.</p>
            <p>Nay, it is no dishonour for God to cast the eye of his providence upon the alteration even of the meanest things: for <hi>who is like,</hi> sayes the Psalmist, <hi>to the Lord our God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 113. ver. 5, 6.</note>
               <hi>who hath his dwelling on high, and yet humbles himself to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:34421:19"/> the things in Heaven and Earth?</hi> Not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to behold the things in Heaven, which is a great condescension to him,<note place="margin">1 Reg. 8. vers. 27.</note>
               <hi>whom the Heaven and the Heaven of Heavens cannot contain;</hi> but also the things in Earth. Now how unworthy these are of his taking notice of, you may see by those diminutive expressions of them compared with Gods greatnesse, <hi>Isa.</hi> 40.15. where the Prophet saies, <hi>Behold, the Nations are but as the drop of a Bucket, and are counted as the small dust of the Ballance; Behold, he takes up the Isles as a very little thing.</hi> And if this be not low enough for them, he sayes further, verse 17. That <hi>all Nations before him are as nothing, and are counted to him as lesse then nothing.</hi> Now look what a wide difference there is betwixt the Sea and a Bucket of water, yea the Drop of a Bucket; or betwixt a heap of dust, and the small dust of the ballance; betwixt very great and very little; betwixt all things and nothing at all, yea lesse then nothing, (if lesse could be:) so vast is the disproportion betwixt God and all Nations, which are the greatest among all earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things. And yet for all this, is God pleas'd so farre to extenuate his own Greatnesse, and to take off from it, as to look after them, and run them about in their severall stages from one point unto another.</p>
            <p>And if you would have this truth to be made out further unto you, our <hi>Saviour</hi> doth it <hi>Matt.</hi> 10.29. by two severall instances.</p>
            <p>The one is of two Sparrows, which are lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle birds and of small value; but the <hi>Greek</hi> yet runs it more diminutively,<note place="margin">Diminutivum à <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> two little sparrows;
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:34421:19"/> and so they must needs be, for they were sold both even for a Farthing, and this is price little enough. Yet the <hi>Arabick</hi> makes it lesse, and hath for it <hi>Phals,</hi> which is the least piece of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney that can be; and accordingly expresses the two Mites spoken of <hi>Mark</hi> 12.42. (which make both but one Farthing) by <hi>Phalsain</hi> in the duall number, as a late and learned Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitor notes.<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> in locum.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The other is of the Haires upon our Heads,<note place="margin">Our haires are things slighted even to a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb, <hi>Ne pili facio;</hi> Erasm. Adag. <hi>sub loco commun. contemptus &amp; vilitatis.</hi>
               </note> being a kind of Excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment belonging to our bodies, &amp; no integrall or necessitous part of them, (as the Heart, Hands and Feet are;) and yet he tells us that God numbers these, and takes such a particular account of them, that not one of them falls to the ground without his dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sall.</p>
            <p>In the vision of the Wheels we read of a wheel within a wheel.<note place="margin">Ezek. 1.16.</note> Now the wheel with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is the wheel of Gods Providence, that turns about the wheels of all outward things, be they never so low and mean. For as God doth not labour in doing the greatest things, so nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth he disdain, either to do or undo the least; but as he <hi>made the small and great,</hi> (saies the book of <hi>Wisdome</hi>) so also doth he <hi>care for both alike.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Wisd. 6.7.</note> The Potter having power over his Clay,<note place="margin">Rom. 9.21.</note> either to make of it a vessel of honour or dishonour, and being made, either to preserve it in that form and being he hath bestowed upon
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:34421:20"/> it, or else to deform and destroy it, since it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitable that every one should do with his own as he pleases. Nay, as he saies of the gnat, that <hi>Nusquam potentior natura quam in minimis;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pliny nar. Hist.</note> So may we say, that God doth no wayes ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance his Power and Wisdome more, then in ordering of the least accidents to be disposed of to his Glory, and the good of his Children. And so much for the <hi>Principall</hi> Efficient cause.</p>
            <p>The <hi>lesse Principall</hi> follows; which (as I said) is either <hi>Impulsive</hi> or <hi>Instrumentall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the <hi>Impulsive</hi> cause of all Changes and Alterations is the sinne of man. This usher'd them in at the first, and so it doth still. For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Adam</hi> sinned, he injoyed a Paradise of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant and uninterrupted happinesse; but so soon as he sins against God, then follows a great change presently:<note place="margin">Gen. 3.16.17.</note> For the Earth all fruitfull be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, now becomes barren, himself subject to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, his wife to travail and sorrow, and both to cares and troubles, to weaknesse and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solution. And so it is also with Nations and Kingdomes. If they be chang'd at any time, sinne is the cause of it; and the greater their sinne is, the greater usually is their change. Great sinnings are the floud-gates to let in great Alterations upon them. For it is not a bare sinning in a Nation, (from which there is none that could ever plead exemption,) but a sinning in some high measure, that is an in-let to Changes in the highest kind. Which made <hi>David</hi> say <hi>Psal.</hi> 107.34. That <hi>a fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full land is turn'd into barrennesse for the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednesse of those that dwell therein.</hi> which the vulgar <hi>Latine</hi> reads <hi>Propter malitiam, i. e.</hi> for
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:34421:20"/> the <hi>malicious wickednesse</hi> of those that dwell therein; which notes a sin of a high nature, <hi>viz.</hi> such a one as is persisted in both against Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge &amp; Conscience. And therefore it is a good ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation which <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sculus</hi> hath upon the words;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Musculus</hi> in locum. Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jusmodi mutationes terra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum non ob id tantum fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt propterea quod homines peccant, (id quod fit toto terrarum orbe) sed quod malitiose.</note>
               <q>These strange Alterations, sayes he, of Nations and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, are not for the sinning of them, (from which no Nation can be free) but for their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious sinning.</q> And this you may see further in <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> Ezek. 21. where we read of a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great Judgement that should befall her from the <hi>Babylonian, viz.</hi> Utter Destruction, expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed by the threefold Overturn wherewith God threatens her vers. 27. And vers. 24. he laies down the Impulsive cause that mov'd him to it; and this is an impudent and shamelesse sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning against God: for they did not commit their sinne in a corner, as those that were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sham'd of it, but (brazen-faced Wretches as they were) they declar'd their sinne as <hi>Sodom,</hi> and discover'd it openly in the face of the sun: and this they did too not only in one or two particular acts, but generally, says the Text, in all their doings.</p>
            <p>Now there is some hope of a modest and bashfull, but none at all of a shamelesse and obdurate Sinner. Thus the Father, when his Sonne hath done amisse, yet is he well perswaded of his amendment,<note place="margin">Erubuit, salva res est. <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent. in Heautont.</hi>
               </note> if he
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:34421:21"/> but see him once blush upon his reproving of him.<note place="margin">Jer. 3.3.</note> But when like <hi>Judah,</hi> he hath once a whores forehead, and refuses to be ashamed, then doth he give him over as a lost child, and not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd.</p>
            <p>So that from hence we see, that in what place soever we find such a Turn, such an Eversion as this, where all is turn'd upside down) there hath been without question some great <hi>Aversio a Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atore ad Creaturam,</hi> some great sinning against God (as the Schoolmen call it.) Which was the reason that when the <hi>English</hi> were (now upon their quitting of <hi>France,</hi> in <hi>Henry</hi> the sixth's dayes) demanded of the <hi>French</hi> by way of derision,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heilens</hi> Geogr. in descript. of <hi>France.</hi>
               </note> when they would make their return thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; it was feelingly answered by one of our nation thus, <hi>When your sinnes are greater then ours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is sinne then that ruines particular Persons, that subverts Families, that periods Kingdomes, that wheels about Governments, that overturns States, that disjoints Commonweales, and sayes unto them as to the proud waves,<note place="margin">Job 38.11.</note>
               <hi>Thus farre ye shall go, and no further.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And so I have done with the Impulsive Cause, and come next to the Instrumentall cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, or means which God uses in effecting his Changes here; and they are two.</p>
            <p>The first is the Motion and Influences of the Celestiall Bodies.</p>
            <p>And this will the better appear, if we consider their forcible workings upon the Mind of man. For though they cannot work immediately upon it, because it is immateriall; yet may
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:34421:21"/> they, and do work mediately upon it, as by the Body, which is the Instrument of the Soul to work by, and the Case wherein it is put up here for a time; and so make it either well or ill affected, according to the Bodies present temper. By which means it comes to passe many times, that not only the dispositions of particular men, but also of whole multitudes collected together in a politick body, are much alter'd and chang'd, either to Labour or Sloth, to Peace or Disquiet, to good or evill actings, according as they are inclin'd by the motions of the Heavenly Bodies.</p>
            <p>And that these Celestiall Bodies have their energy upon all Sublunary things, is plain,</p>
            <p>First, by Scripture; as <hi>Job</hi> 38.33. where the Lord speaks thus to <hi>Job, Know'st thou the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of Heaven? and canst thou set the dominion thereof in the Earth?</hi> which implies,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Heavens have power and domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in the Earth.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That this power of theirs is set them from Gods ordinance and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment.<note place="margin">Astra regunt homines, sed regit Astra Deus.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, by the constant Observation and Experience of all Ages.<note place="margin">In lib. 4, de Rep. cap. 2.</note>
               <hi>Bodinus</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Lawyer speaks well to this point; Many erre (sayes he) greatly, who think the influence of the Celestiall Spheres to be nothing, whenas their strength hath ever been most effectual, as in Sacred Writ is to be seen: &amp; he cites the 38. chap. of <hi>Job</hi> before mentioned to prove the same. Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding further, that many ancient Writers have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the great changes in Cities &amp; Kingdomes upon
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:34421:22"/> the conjunction of the superiour Planets, but to them only where they have been deputed of God to that end and purpose. And that they have been instrumentall towards the working of such effects, he shewes by an induction of some particular instances; As that before the translation of the <hi>Roman</hi> Soveraignty unto <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sar,</hi> there was a great conjunction of the su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour Planets met together in <hi>Scorpio:</hi> which fell out again seven hundred yeares after, when the <hi>Arabian</hi> Legions receiv'd the law of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet,</hi> rebell'd against the <hi>Greek</hi> Emperours, &amp; subdued the Eastern <hi>Asia</hi> from the <hi>Christians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The same also came about again <hi>anno Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sti</hi> 1464. after which <hi>Ladamachus</hi> King of the <hi>Tartars</hi> was by his Subjects thrust out of the chair of Soveraignty, and <hi>Friderick</hi> the third driven out of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary</hi> by <hi>Matthias Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Qui volet, in eodem ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pite plura legat.</note> who from a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soner stept up to the Royall Throne, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Alstedius</hi> (vir undequaque doctus) ait conjunctionem <hi>Saturni</hi> &amp; <hi>Jovis</hi> in Ariete (igneae triplicitatis signo) Anno Christi <hi>1642.</hi> novi a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licujus imperii revolutionem portendere; cujus effectum verisimile est, nos in nuperis ab eo tempore motibus &amp; mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tationibus in <hi>Anglia</hi> nostra, satis super{que} vidisse, necdum videmus terminari. <hi>Nunt. Prophetic.</hi> pag. <hi>34.</hi>
               </note>And <hi>Alstedius</hi> tells us, that the Conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter</hi> in February 1642. did foretell and portend the revoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of some new Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire and Government to fall out after it in <hi>Europe.</hi> The effect whereof in part (its like) we have seen in this nation alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:34421:22"/> and may live (if God so dispose of us) to see further of it yet in time to come.</p>
            <p>But to passe this, and to come to that daily and usuall course of Gods proceedings with us in the world. Here methinks there should be few, (though of ordinary capacities among us) but (if we be a little observing) may see this truth made good by the eye of our own expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, which tells us that the earth is either fruitfull or barren, and the air either wholsome or infectious, suitably to that measure and manner of influence they receive from them.</p>
            <p>And therefore when God will at any time bring about some great change in the world, it is then easy to see how usually he fits his inferiour means, according to their severall na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, for the orderly transacting of it in those stations wherein he hath set them. As when he will turn a fruitfull land into barrennesse, and again, a barren land into fruitfulnesse, (which he promis'd his own people, <hi>Hos.</hi> 2.21.) there he tells them in what order he will work it; <hi>I will hear</hi> (says he) <hi>the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, and they shall hear the Earth, and they shall hear</hi> Jezreel. For this is a sure rule, That the supreme cause of all doth not take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the natures and workings of secondary causes, but rather establish them: which is the reason of that speech of God to <hi>Job</hi> in the ordinary revolution of the times and seasons of the year, <hi>Job</hi> 38.31. <hi>Canst thou bind the sweet influences of the</hi> Pleiades, <hi>and loose the bonds of</hi> Orion?</p>
            <p>Now the <hi>Pleiades</hi> are those we commonly call the Seven Starres, that have their influence
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:34421:23"/> on the earth by producing sweet showres to the opening and refreshing of it, about the Spring of the year, and <hi>Orion</hi> is a Constellation most conspicuous in the Winter season, as having a commissionary power to bind up the earth with Frosts. Again, <hi>canst thou bring forth</hi> Mazza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roth <hi>in his season; i. e.</hi> the twelve Signes succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sively after one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;<note place="margin">Quid de his stellis subtili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us dicant Astronomi, non est hic nostrum tractare ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curatius: tantum dicemus id quod locus hic postulat, non ab alio quam Deo vim illam stellis pluviam &amp; frigus generandi datam. <hi>Sanct. in Job.</hi>
               </note>) <hi>or guide</hi> Arctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus <hi>with his Sons? (i. e.</hi> the Polar starre, as some will have it, with those <hi>ignes minores</hi> that wait upon him; or <hi>Bootes,</hi> as others. It is not then so much the Earth, as the Heavens that give us either fruit, or withhold it; they being the first ordinary means, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by God uses to work out alterations in subluna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry things.</p>
            <p>The second Instrumentall cause of these strange Vicissitudes here below, is the Will of Man; For though it have not a liberty to spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, yet all grant it a liberty to externall acts, and morall goodnesse. And this Liberty of mans will doth God use as an under-wheel to turn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout most of those Alterations that are in the world.</p>
            <p>It is true, that health and sicknesse, peace and warre, plenty and scarcity, riches and poverty, proceed from God as the principall Efficient cause; but yet for all this we deny not but that God makes use both of our selves and others, as to the means of bringing them about. The life
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:34421:23"/> of <hi>Joseph</hi> was checquer'd with variety of acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents; for he is now a Slave to the <hi>Ismaelites,</hi> and by and by a Prince in <hi>Aegypt.</hi> Now these although they proceeded from God as the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour, yet was the will of his Brethren, as the will of <hi>Reuben</hi> and <hi>Judah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. c. 37.</note> the instruments of preserving his life, and the wills of his other Brethren the meanes of selling him into <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now because it is the Nature of Instruments to be subservient to the Principall Agent,<note place="margin">Instrumentum nisi à prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipali Agente motum, non operatur, <hi>Aquin. 3.</hi> part. Summae quaest. <hi>62.</hi> Art. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> and to be determin'd by it; therefore give me leave here by the way to fasten this exhortation upon you, That in all Changes whatsoever you will look beyond the Instruments of them, unto God the Principall Agent. For so did <hi>Job</hi> in his losses, beyond the plundring <hi>Chaldeans</hi> and <hi>Sabeans,</hi> unto <hi>Dominus abstulit, The Lord hath given, and the Lord hath taken away;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 1.21.</note> looking upon them as we use to do upon an <hi>Index, tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum in ordine ad Librum,</hi> only in order to the Book it self, <hi>et in transitu ad Deum,</hi> in his pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage unto God, who sets them awork, as to their naturall powers and faculties, though to the evill of them no otherwise, then by or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering and over-ruling it to the good of his Children. And hence it is that the wicked are call'd Gods Sword, as in the 17 <hi>Psalm</hi> verse 13. <hi>Deliver my soul</hi> (saies <hi>David) from the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked which is thy Sword.</hi> And so must we in all those Losses that befall us here, have in our eye not so much the Sword, as the Hand that holds
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:34421:24"/> it; which will be one means, and a good one too, to bring us to <hi>Davids</hi> calm temper in the 39. <hi>Psal.</hi> 19. who saies in the like condition, That <hi>he was dumb, and did not open his mouth,</hi> nor let fall an impatient word in it, because it was Gods doing: And therefore when <hi>Abishai</hi> would have taken away <hi>Shimei's</hi> life for cursing of <hi>David,</hi> No, (sayes he) <hi>Let him alone, Jussit enim Dominus, for the Lord hath bidden him curse;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Sam. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.11.</note>
               <hi>who then shall say, Wherefore hast thou done so? q. d.</hi> Who then dare expostulate with God, or call him to account about it, as if he were unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous in it; since evill men are but Swords in Gods hand, who, when he hath once done his work by them, will either put them up again into his Scabbard, and lay them by, or else so blunt the edge of their power, that it shall not cut, or else break them a pieces, and throw them quite away? And so much for the Efficient Causes of Vicissitudes.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Next I shall speak to the Ends, or Finall Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of them.</p>
            <p>And these are either <hi>Ex parte Dei,</hi> or <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stri;</hi> In respect of God, or our selves.</p>
            <p>First, In respect of God; and so the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall End why God rings such Changes upon all earthly things, and will have them disposed of after so various a manner, is to make them by it the more tunable to his own Glory, which by this meanes is exceedingly magnify'd, and advanc'd: but especially in the Attributes of his Power, Truth, Wisdome and Goodnesse.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In his Power and Omnipotency: that so he may let the world know, that the Finger of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:34421:24"/> his Power is in all transactions; and that he can do whatsoever he will, both in heaven and earth, and yet changes not.</p>
            <p>For why else did God work so many mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous Changes in <hi>Aegypt</hi> by the hand of <hi>Moses?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why turn'd he <hi>Moses</hi> Rod into a Serpent, and the <hi>Aegyptian</hi> Waters into Bloud?</p>
            <p>Why their Dust into Lice and Flies, and their Light into Darknesse for the space of three dayes together?</p>
            <p>Why else created he a new generation of Frogs and Locusts among them?</p>
            <p>Why unheard of diseases upon themselves and upon their cattell?</p>
            <p>Why destroyed he their Herbs and Fruit-trees with Hail, and their First-born with untimely death?</p>
            <p>In a word, Why caus'd he the Red-sea to go out of its naturall course and chanell, whereby it became a wall to the <hi>Israelites,</hi> and a grave to the <hi>Aegyptians?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Did not God all this to make known the glory of his power, in the preservation of the one and destruction of the other? Yes;<note place="margin">Exod. 9.16.</note>
               <hi>For this cause</hi> (sayes God to <hi>Moses) I have raised thee up, to shew in thee my power, and that my name may be declared in all the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. He advances also his Glory this way, by manifesting his Truth and Faithfulness: in that those things which are accidentall in regard of us, and seem as impossible, yet are they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly brought to passe in their due times and seasons. As in the bringing of the <hi>Israelites</hi> out of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> wherein God was full as good as his
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:34421:25"/> word, and kept touch with them to a day in their Deliverance; as you may see <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.41. where we read, That <hi>it came to passe in the end of four hundred and thirty years, even the self-same day it came to passe, that all the hosts of the Lord went out of the land of Aegypt.</hi> All <hi>Pharaoh's</hi> oppositions and tergiversations could not prorogue their Bondage so much as one day beyond the time prefix'd of God, but serv'd only to fill up that <hi>Interim,</hi> or void space of time betwixt Gods Promise made to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his performance of it.<note place="margin">Gen. 15.13.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And if you ask by what intervalls of time the truth of this promise came about so punctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally,<note place="margin">Vide nuperrimas Anno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tationes in <hi>Gen. 15.13.</hi>
               </note> Divines will tell you, That from <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham's</hi> receiving of the promise, unto the birth of <hi>Isaac,</hi> were five and twenty years; sixty from thence to <hi>Jacobs</hi> birth; and to his death (which fell out presently upon their entrance into <hi>Aegypt</hi>) a hundred and thirty yeares. After which unto the death of <hi>Levi,</hi> who was <hi>Ultimus Patriarcharum,</hi> the last of the Patriarchs that survived, and in which space the <hi>Israelites</hi> were kindly entreated for <hi>Joseph's</hi> sake, were ninety four years; and a hundred and one and twenty more of cruell Bondage, untill <hi>Moses</hi> came to deliver them from it in the reign of <hi>Pharaoh Cencres.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All which particulars being gathered up to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, do make up the complete summe of four hundred and thirty yeares, and may serve to justify God in all his sayings, and to clear his truth in the least circumstance and pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctilio
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:34421:25"/> of time, when it shall come to be judged.</p>
            <p>For when once Gods appointed time is come to introduce a change, either for better or worse, among any people, then shall eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry breath of wind, how crosse soever it seems to blow at the present, yet be so farre from hindering Gods work in it, as that one way or other you shall find it in the sequel, to contribute its help and assistance to it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. God advances also his Glory this way, in the manifestation of his Wisdome and Goodnesse; in that he makes a sweet har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of so many different cords and chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and frames a most admirable Order out of a seeming Disorder and Confusion.</p>
            <p>Many and diverse are the qualities of Herbs, yet if a skilfull Simpler hath the mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them, he knows how to make of them a well-relish'd and wholsome Sallade: So, many were the interchangeable passages that happen'd to <hi>Joseph;</hi> and had we the same, it may be we should think them very confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed ones; but yet let the Wisdome and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of God but lay them together, and we shall presently find, as <hi>Joseph</hi> did, the close of them all in a sweet <hi>diapason.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For though all things, as to us, are float<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up and down, to and again, by chance as it were and accident; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">G. <hi>Nazian.</hi> in Invect. in <hi>Julianum.</hi>
               </note> sayes <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory Nazianzen;</hi> yet if we look to the order and appointment of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:34421:26"/> Gods Providence, (which doth alwayes most wisely contrive all events for the good of his Children,) they are fixt and stable, howbeit they may seem to go contrary at the present.</p>
            <p>And of Gods dealing in this kind we have <hi>Job</hi> an eminent example; who is to day the greatest man for Wealth and Honour in all the East, (and a tablet of this his Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse you may see in his nine and twentieth chapter, which I desire you to read over at your leisure,) wherein you shall find a whole <hi>series</hi> of worldly Prosperity to wait upon him;) yet to morrow he is poor, even to a by-word and proverb,<note place="margin">Chap. 30.</note>
               <hi>As poor as</hi> Job: insomuch as he spends all the next chapter in bemoaning his suddain change, beginning it with a <hi>But;</hi> which though a small monosyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable, yet as the Helme of a Ship turns a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the vessel any way, so doth this <hi>But</hi> turn about <hi>Job</hi> and all his former Honour and Prosperity, into the extremest contempt and adversity.<note place="margin">Job 30. verse 1.</note>
               <hi>But now,</hi> sayes he, <hi>they that are younger then I have me in derision, whose fathers I would have disdained to have set with the dogs of my Flock;</hi> and ending it with this dolefull accent, verse last, <hi>versa est cithara mea in luctum, &amp; organum in vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem flentium; My harp is turned into mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and my organ into the voice of those that weep.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet all is well (we say) that ends well; and so it was with <hi>Job,</hi> which makes Saint <hi>James</hi> say by way of support unto Gods
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:34421:26"/> people in their afflictions,<note place="margin">James 5.11.</note>
               <hi>Ye have heard of the patience of</hi> Job, <hi>and have seen the end of the Lord; i. e.</hi> what good end God gave him in it; for the next day God brings a great deal of Light out of this Darknesse, by a wise and gracious disposing of all that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill to him for the best,<note place="margin">Job last, verse 12.</note> in giving him twice as much as he had at the first, and blessing his later end more then his beginning.</p>
            <p>So that although for a time all those sad Changes that befell <hi>Job,</hi> seem'd even to crosse the ordinary course of Gods care and Providence to him; yet in the conclusion you see how his Wisedome and Goodnesse cut them all out, and made them serve to his greater Honour and Abundance.</p>
            <p>And so much for the Ends or Finall Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses in respect of God.</p>
            <p>They follow now in respect of our selves.</p>
            <p>And these are two: first to confirm our Faith; secondly to reform our lives, and to work out by them good to his servants.</p>
            <p>First, to confirm our Faith.</p>
            <p>And so God brings many times great Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges into the world, to try, if amidst those shakings of outward things among us, we will be shaken in our Faith, or not. That as the Apostle speakes of heresies 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.19. <hi>Oportet esse Haereses, There must be He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resies among you, that they which are appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved may be made manifest;</hi> so say I, <hi>Oportet esse mutationes,</hi> There must be Changes: and these not so much in respect of the things themselves, which are in their own natures
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:34421:27"/> liable to alteration and dissolution; as in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of Gods end in it, that they which are approved and sincere in the faith, may be manifested to be so, by their constancy and perseverance in it. That as there is a neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sity of Fire to try Gold, whether it be true or else counterfeit; so also is there a neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sity of Changes: for by these it will appear, whether we will measure our Religion by outward things, and in the losse or enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of them be lost in our Protestant Faith, yea or no.</p>
            <p>There is nothing, Beloved, more discovers the Hypocrite then his <hi>Ingenium versatile,</hi> (as <hi>Livy</hi> said of <hi>Cato</hi>) then his turning hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour in Religion: for which I do not say he shall be plagued in Hell,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plutarch</hi> feigns <hi>Thespe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sius</hi> returning from Hell, and telling (among other things he saw there infli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted on evill men) that hypocrites were there pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished by turning up and down continually. <hi>Plut.</hi> De his qui sero puniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, pag. <hi>203.</hi>
               </note> by being wheel'd about there continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly without any relaxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, (though that may seem a punishment somewhat suitable to his Weathercock-dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position here upon earth;) no, <hi>Hoc ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis Ethnicum,</hi> This is too heathenish: but rather with the Prophet <hi>David,</hi> That <hi>he shall turn into Hell with all those that forget God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 9.17.</note> which is that portion of Hypocrites mention'd by our Saviour <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. last.</p>
            <p>For if an Apple be rotten at the coare, it will not hold long upon the Tree, but upon the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:34421:27"/> least Wind will fall from it. And so it is with the rotten-hearted Hypocrite; if a little crosse wind do but blow up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, oh how soon doth he fall off from the tree of Life, and become a wind-fall in his Religion, for the Devil that old Serpent to prey upon!</p>
            <p>Every Cock-boat (you know) will bear up well enough in a calm sea: but that is a stout Vessell that can live in the most troubled water.<note place="margin">Vid. <hi>Cyprian</hi> de lapsis; &amp; <hi>Fox</hi> Martyr. <hi>p. 1362.</hi>
               </note> And too too many there were in the Primitive times that, like D<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Pendleton</hi> in Queen <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> dayes, boasted much of their Constancy in the Orthodox Faith during <hi>Constantines</hi> dayes, so long as God hedg'd about his Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard with Peace and Prosperity; but so soon as that Hedge was broken down,<note place="margin">Psalm 80.12. and 13 verses.</note> and erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous, yea hereticall Doctrines were let in like so many Beasts of prey to devoure, then how quickly did these prove Turncoats, and Apostates from the Faith!</p>
            <p>But as for the true Christian, he is like a Rock —<hi>mediis immotus in undis:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Virgil.</note> That al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the waves are alwaies swelling against him, yet is he the same man still in his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Religion, and wavers not: or else like that House built upon the Rock,<note place="margin">Mat 25.7.</note> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst which the Flouds came, and the Winds blew, but it fell not, because it was built up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Rock.</p>
            <p>And such a well-built house was Saint <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sil,</hi> who being threatned with death by <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lens</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:34421:28"/> if he would not advise further and turn <hi>Arrian,</hi> answer'd with this brave resolution,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sozom. hist. lib. 6. c. 16.</hi> In hoc mihi consilio non est opus: nam idem qui jam sum, cras etiam fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turus sum.</note>
               <q>I need not any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther advice then I have taken already about this matter; for to morrow I shall be the same man that I am to day therein, and no other.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And here know that some things are of Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity, wherein we cannot but change, as in naturall, civill and morall things, and to change in these is only humane.</p>
            <p>Others again are of Duty: and these either prohibited, or enjoyn'd.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Prohibited, as in evill and erroneous things: and to change here is pious and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine; and not to change, either Weaknesse or Obstinacy.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Enjoyn'd, as in sacred and religious: and to change here is impious and Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolicall; and not to change, true Christian Fortitude and Constancy.</p>
            <p>Whatsoever things we see then wheeling about in the world, as Governments, Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies and the like, nay howsoever we may change our selves or be chang'd in somethings of an indifferent nature, by those that have dominion over our Bodies and Estates; yet is there no man that hath dominion over our Faith:<note place="margin">2 Cor. 1. last.</note> But this is Gods peculiar, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in this we must not change.</p>
            <p>It is not with saving Truths as it is
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:34421:28"/> with Clothes, which alter every year as the fashion doth:<note place="margin">1 John 2.17.</note> for <hi>the fashion of the world pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses away</hi> (sayes Saint <hi>John;</hi>) but true Religion is ever in fashion with good men and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters not.</p>
            <p>And herein we may justly take occasion to bewail the unsteadinesse of some in these times, who are mere <hi>Scepticks</hi> in Religion, alwayes conceiving some new Opinions in it, and alwayes in pain till they be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd of their new conceptions, though never so <hi>monstrous</hi> and <hi>deformed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That which was truth with them yester<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day,<note place="margin">The <hi>Magdeburgenses</hi> tell us <hi>Cent. 4. c. 11.</hi> that such was <hi>Eustathius</hi> Bishop of <hi>Sebaste,</hi> who was one day for the <hi>Homousian,</hi> and another for the <hi>Homoiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sian</hi> Confession, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly as they suited best with his present turn.</note> is no such thing to day; and what is so to day is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise to morrow; such Changelings there be in this last Age, who like the Moon do ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver appear the same two dayes together! <q>And I would to God,<note place="margin">Atque utinam vel sic mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentur: Haec enim cito ad plenitudinem suam redit, hi vero nec sero conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuntur. <hi>Ambros.</hi> Pro va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riis actionibus <hi>conc. 4.</hi> in <hi>Tom. 5.</hi>
                  </note> sayes Saint <hi>Ambrose,</hi> that their change were no worse then that of the Moon; for she returns a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain within a little time to her full light, but these never.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And he is blind that sees not this among us, (namely) how some turn every day to
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:34421:29"/>
               <hi>Popish</hi> Superstition, but more to <hi>Anabaptisti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call</hi> Fancies; some unto <hi>Socinian</hi> Blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, but most unto <hi>Atheisticall</hi> Notions, and all into Sensuality; this being the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Sewer into which all the former run, and are ultimately resolved.</p>
            <p>But as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> said to his <hi>Galathians,</hi> so do I to such,<note place="margin">Galat. 3.1.</note>
               <hi>O foolish</hi> Galathians, <hi>who hath bewitch'd you that you should not obey the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel?</hi> And it is a metaphor, sayes one,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leighs</hi> Annotat. in locum.</note> from Sorcerers, who use to cast a mist before the peoples eyes, that so they may not take a right view of what is presented to them: As if he had said, Who hath cast a mist before the eyes of your understandings, to make that appear unto you for truth which indeed is not? What? <hi>Are ye so foolish, that having begun in the spirit, ye will be perfected in the flesh?</hi> So, Are ye so foolish, that having begun in truth, ye will end in falshood? or can ye be so simple, as to exchange Gold for Dirt, Wheat for Chaffe, and your pretious Faith, as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> calls it,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.1. Heb. 11.1.</note> which is the substance of things hoped for, for Errours of all sorts, and mere shadows of Truth? I trow not. For if Errour (as our <hi>Kingly Divine</hi> said well) have any advantage,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, pag. 137.</note> it consists in No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velty: or if Truth any, it consists in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stancy.</p>
            <p>Was the Doctrine then of the Reformed Churches, and the Harmony of our Confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions grounded upon evident and pregnant
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:34421:29"/> Scriptures, maintain'd by the Orthodox and primitive Fathers, and conveyed to us by the constant tradition of the universall Church, the Faith of Christ once deliver'd to the Saints, and the Truth of God yesterday? why, so it is to day, and will be to morrow also. And therefore to day in our profession of it we must be as yesterday, and to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row as this day:<note place="margin">Heb. 13.8.</note> because as God is the same yesterday, to day, and for ever; so also is the Truth of God, That which was once so,<note place="margin">Veritas Dei una semper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que sui similis: In prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fat. aed <hi>Harm. Confes.</hi>
               </note> will be so alwayes, and cannot be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise.</p>
            <p>Oh that we would then be exhorted in the <hi>Apostles</hi> words,<note place="margin">Ephes. 4.14.</note> To <hi>stand fast in the Faith, to quit our selves like men, and be strong: and not to be as children,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phora a rota, quae motu continuo circumacta par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes summas &amp; imas sem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per commutat, <hi>Pareus in locum.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>toss'd to and fro, and carried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with every wind of Doctrine;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.20.</note>
               <hi>but to be as men in understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, stedfast and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveable;</hi> that so God may have cause to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry on our behalf, as he did on <hi>Jobs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 2.5.</note>
               <hi>Hast thou consider'd</hi> (sayes God to Sathan) <hi>my servant</hi> Job? So, hast thou consider'd such a servant of mine? Seest thou to how many changes I have subjected him? to changes in his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, to changes in his Estate, to changes in his Liberty, to changes in his Friends and Acquaintance? Nay, seest thou how many
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:34421:30"/> of his Brethren are chang'd of late, from a fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brish distemper before, now into a sleepy le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thargy? Seest thou how indifferent they are for their religion round about him, and how many shaken reeds there are on every side of him?<note place="margin">Nec iratum colere desti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit numen. <hi>Sen.</hi> ad <hi>Marc. cap. 13.</hi>
               </note> And yet for all this, as my ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant <hi>Job</hi> did, so doth he still hold his integrity. But enough of this.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Gods end also in it is, To re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form our lives, and do us good by his so va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious dispensations to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us.<note place="margin">Huic affine est illud <hi>Amos 9. v. 9.</hi> ubi duo conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randa; vel purgatum frumentum à sordibus, vel exagitatum à cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brante, dum ab uno cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bri latere in alterum pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellitur. <hi>Sanct.</hi> in locum.</note> Hence we read <hi>Isa.</hi> 30.28. of a sieve of vanity, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in God sayes he will sift the Nations, and shake them to and fro one after another, that so he may winnow them from that Chaffe of sinne that is within them. For why was <hi>Moab at ease from his youth?</hi> why <hi>settled he upon his lees,</hi> and held still his <hi>corrupt taste?</hi> but because he was never disquieted, nor <hi>emptied from vessel to vessel,</hi> Jer. 48.11. Thus a sedentary life we find very subject to Diseases; and a long standing Prosperity to a Nation, is like a standing Pool, whose water doth soon puddle and putrify. And this is the reason of that speech of <hi>David</hi> Psal. 55.19. <hi>Because they have no Changes therefore they fear not God;</hi> making by it the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:34421:30"/> uncheckt prosperity of worldly men a great occasion of their continuance in sinne, and so an <hi>Index</hi> of Gods Wrath upon them, rather then of his speciall Favour to them.</p>
            <p>And therefore now we have seen the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel of God moving the waters of this Church and State by intestine Warre, new Opinions in Religion, by Sects, divisions and the like; it will be good for us to meditate, how God hereby intends to purge us from that sinfull filth that adheres to us as our disrespect to Gods Ministers, and contempt of his Word, our Cruelty and Oppression, our Pride and Security, our Worldly-mindednesse and Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrisie.</p>
            <p>Indeed men, who are the instruments of them, may have other ends in such Alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as to wreak their own spleen upon their adversaries, to unhorse others, and get them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves into the saddle either of Profit or Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment; (That as <hi>Demetrius</hi> the Silver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>smith said, <hi>We get our gaines by this means;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 19.25.</note> so say they, We get our Honours and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>states by these means, for if the waters had not been troubled, we had catch'd nothing;) or else to satisfy their own corrupt wills and pleasures; as the Authour to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> sayes of earthly parents,<note place="margin">Hebrews 12.10.</note> That they chasten their children after their own pleasure, but God who is the supreme Agent, he doth it for our profit, and not his own; there being no ends of gold and silver, no mere will or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge in his end, but only our profit,<note place="margin">Prov. 25.4.</note> and to take away the drosse from the silver, that
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:34421:31"/> so he may bring forth (to use <hi>Solomon</hi>'s expression) a <hi>Vas electum</hi> a chosen Vessel,<note place="margin">Prov. 25.4. Acts 9.15.</note> as S. <hi>Paul</hi> was, and fit for the Finer.</p>
            <p>Thus the Scripture tells us of <hi>Joseph,</hi> how he was pass'd over from his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren to the <hi>Ismaelites,</hi> and from them to <hi>Potiphar;</hi> and his brethren had one end in it, but God another: for they did it for evil against him,<note place="margin">Gen. last, ver. 20.</note> (as he tells them himself,) and to get twenty Pieces by the sale of him; but as for God, he meant it to him for good, and to save much people alive.</p>
            <p>And so also was <hi>Christ</hi> the Antitype of <hi>Joseph,</hi> thrust (as we say) from post to pillar, <hi>viz.</hi> from <hi>Judas</hi> to <hi>Caiaphas,</hi> from him to <hi>Pilate,</hi> from <hi>Pilate</hi> to <hi>Herod,</hi> from <hi>Herod</hi> back again to <hi>Pilate,</hi> and then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of the clamorous and unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable multitude to be crucified: and <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> had one end in <hi>Christ's</hi> death, but God another. The end of <hi>Judas</hi> in it was to silver his bagge with thirty Pieces,<note place="margin">Mat 26.9.</note> but Gods end was to satisfy his own Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice, and to save mankind by it.</p>
            <p>So that let mens sinfull ends in these Changes and Alterations be what they will, yet is Gods end in it the gaining of glory to himself, by his taking away that sinne and corruption which he sees contracted in us by a long standing secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:34421:31"/> And if these changes of his be not as a gentle fire to purify us, they shall be as a consuming fire to destroy us.</p>
            <p>And so much for the Efficient and Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall causes of Vicissitudes.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Uses</hi> follow; And they are three.</p>
            <p>First, To take us off from our greedy desire of worldly things.</p>
            <p>Secondly, To unpride us in a prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous condition.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, To comfort and support us in an afflicted one.</p>
            <p>And to this purpose there is a good say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Marcus Aurelius Antoninus</hi> the best of all the Heathen Emperours, which is this,</p>
            <p>
               <q>Meditate (sayes he) with thy self how swiftly all things that subsist are car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away:<note place="margin">In his Meditat. trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated by <hi>Merric Casau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon</hi> lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>19.</hi>
                  </note> for both the substances them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves are in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall flux, and all actions in a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall change, yea the causes of them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so subject to a thousand alterations, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is there any thing that can be said to be settled or at a stand.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>And from hence he draws this inference:
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:34421:32"/> Art thou not then unwise, who for these things art either distracted with cares, puff'd up too much with pride, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected with troubles?</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Use </seg>1</label> And it may put many of us Christians to the blush, who seldome make so good use of it as this Heathen did, though we have a farre clearer light then he had to guide us to it.</p>
            <p>First then, the consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of this point, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Brevis est &amp; caduca hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus seculi gloria: igitur despice transitoria, ut habeas aeterna. <hi>Bern.</hi> lib. de mod. vivend. Serm. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> The great Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cissitude and Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>constancy of all earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things, may serve to wean our hearts from the pleasing teat of this World, and to raise them up to that place where on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fixed good is found.</p>
            <p>Here we are all too apt with the rich fool to set down our rests, when (God knows) we have little or no cause so to do. <hi>Nescis enim,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Horat.</note>
               <hi>ah nescis serus quid vesper ferat;</hi> Since we do not know what the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wifery of this evening, nay lesse of this hour, or moment may help to bring forth.</p>
            <p>It may be a change of our Estates in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Beggery by Fire, Thieves, and the like; or else of our Liberty into Thraldome; or
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:34421:32"/> of our Health into Sicknesse; all these suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessively wheeling about, untill at last our great change come from Life to Death, and swallow up the rest, as the sea doth the waters that fall into it.</p>
            <p>Alas! here we are subject to a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand casualties; but in Heaven, there, there we shall meet with no such altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions;<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, A Kingdome that is not floating up and down, as earthly Kingdomes are in the sea of this world with every tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pest.</note> for that is a Kingdome that cannot be shaken as earthly Kingdomes are,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.28.</note> either by warre, factions, all-eating time, or the like. No; but there is Peace without War, Quiet without Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, Freedome without Thraldome, Day without Night, Health without Sicknesse, and Life without Death: whereas here it is farre otherwise; for God takes away one it may be,<note place="margin">Hunc necat febribus, illum opprimit doloribus; hunc flammis, illum gla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dio, &amp;c. <hi>Augustin.</hi> in <hi>2</hi> Soliloq.</note> with a Fever, another with the Sword, as S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine</hi> reckons them up. Nay, <hi>he cuts off the spirits of Princes</hi> (sayes the <hi>Psalmist;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 76. ver. 12.</note>) which <hi>Junius</hi> and <hi>Tremelius</hi> translate by <hi>Vindemiat. i. e.</hi> he slips them off as a Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tager doth a Bunch of Grapes from a
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:34421:33"/> Tree, it is so quickly done. Even the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est enterprizes that the greatest Magnifico's of the earth undertake, God doth but blow <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pon them a little with the breath of his displeasure, and how soon are they bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted and shrink away to nothing!</p>
            <p>An example of this we have in <hi>Xerxes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Justin. hist. lib. 2.</note> who went against <hi>Greece</hi> with a million of men, and as many ships as cover'd the <hi>Hellespont;</hi> as if he would have sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued the Sea, have put a hook into her jaws, and have led her away in triumph: yet how soon was his over-bold pride dash'd in pieces by a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of Greeks!<note place="margin">Quem dies vidit veni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens superbum, Hunc dies vidit fugiens jacentem. <hi>Sen.</hi> trag. in <hi>Thyest.</hi> act. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> One and the same day saw him both happy and miserable; using him as a tender and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgent Mother in the morning, but in the evening as a cruell and hard Stepdame.</p>
            <p>Oh the folly then of those that lye al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes sucking at these earthly flowers, which are as various in their shapes, as ever <hi>Proteus</hi> was, and constant in nothing save in their inconstancy!</p>
            <p>It was the saying of <hi>Maximilian</hi> the second, That every year of our life was a
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:34421:33"/> climactericall year, and brought with it some great change or other.</p>
            <p>And if every year be so changeable, what fools then are they that joyn land to land, and house to house, that they may dwell alone in the earth! yea what mean great men to pride it so much in their <hi>Babels</hi> here below, and out of a greedy desire of gain to run out of their own chanels,<note place="margin">Quid quod ultra limites clientium salis avarus, parum locuples continen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te ripa? <hi>Horat.</hi> lib. <hi>2.</hi> ode <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> and to call their lands by their own names? For they that do thus, declare plainly that they think themselves to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy a settled estate here on earth,<note place="margin">Quasi aut nunquam es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent mutabiles, aut vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam coelestem non expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctarent. <hi>Bellarm.</hi> lib. <hi>2.</hi> de aetern. faelicit.</note> as if they should never see a change, or at least did not for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent look for in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven a better and more enduring substance, as the Authour to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> speaks, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.34.</p>
            <p>And yet as the Prophet <hi>Isaiah</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:34421:34"/> so may we, <hi>Quis credidit auditui nostro?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Isa. 53.1.</note>
               <hi>who hath believed our report?</hi> or to whom is this truth of God revealed? For it is strange to see how few among us do believe this, that both in our persons and estates we are so changeable.</p>
            <p>But <hi>this is their way,</hi> sayes <hi>David, this is their foolishnesse.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 49.13.</note>
            </p>
            <p>For how soon did <hi>Galba</hi> start aside from the Empire,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tacit.</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. lib. 6.</note>
               <hi>Degu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stans Imperium,</hi> tasting it only, as <hi>Jonathan</hi> did the Honey with the end of his Spear! How soon was <hi>Haman</hi> chang'd from the Minion of the Court, to be the hang-by of the world!</p>
            <p>Again, how soon was <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> chang'd, even from a man to a Beast; and <hi>Herod</hi> from the highest of men, to be meat even for the lowest of Reptiles? And the prosperity of <hi>Richard</hi> the third was so short (says our incomparable histori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an) that it took end ere himself could well look over it.<note place="margin">Sir <hi>Walt. Rawl.</hi> Pref. to the worlds hist.</note>
               <note place="margin">Ostenditur tantum, non possidetur; &amp; dum pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet, transit; <hi>Sen. Epist. 110.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:34421:34"/>
            <p>There is not any thing then that we can call constant here on earth; which makes the Authour to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> speaking of <hi>Abraham,</hi> say, That <hi>he look'd for a City having foundations:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bellarm.</hi> in eodem loco. Vere civitas coelestis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prie fundamentum ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet, &amp;c.</note> Upon which one gives us this note; That the Heavenly City can on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be said to have properly a Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whereas those Cities that are on earth, do show plainly by their daily ruines that they have no sure foundation to rest upon.</p>
            <p>Oh let this be a means to take off the wheels of our Affections from their eager pursuit after earthly things, and set them upon things above, <hi>where the moth can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not come at them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 6. v. 19.</note>
               <hi>nor thieves break through to steal.</hi> And let us look to that charge of the Apostle, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.17. <hi>Charge those that are rich in the world, that they trust not in uncertain Riches;</hi> or rather in riches which are Uncertainty it self in the abstract; (for so the <hi>Greek</hi> runs it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>i. e.</hi> in the uncertainty of
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:34421:35"/> Riches.) And that we may in no wise doubt of this their uncertainty, the Wise man prefixes a note of certainty before this uncertainty,<note place="margin">Prov. 23.5.</note>
               <hi>Certainly,</hi> (says he) <hi>Riches make themselves wings, and fly away as an Eagle towards heaven:</hi> as if he should have said, Certainly Riches, and all world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things are as uncertain as a Bird that is upon the wing:<note place="margin">Psal. 62.10.</note> and therefore we must not <hi>set our hearts upon them;</hi> but our dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prayer and practice must be, <hi>So to passe through things temporall,</hi>
               <note place="margin">4 Coll. post Trin.</note>
               <hi>that so we do not loose those things that are eternall:</hi> or else with <hi>David</hi> let us beseech God to <hi>incline our hearts unto his Testimonies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 119.36.</note>
               <hi>and not to Covetousnesse.</hi> Now this inclining our hearts unto Gods Testimonies, is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing else but that holy and penitentiall change of heart and life, or else that turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto God with all our hearts, which God calls for at our hands, and expects from us in all his changes, whether per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonall or else nationall. which if he find in us, then let what changes soever fall, they shall all work together for our good: but if not, we must then look to be as a
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:34421:35"/> rowling stone, and to have our daily turns and changes in this life from one de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of misery to another, untill at last we turn into Hell, as <hi>David</hi> speaks, <hi>with all those that forget God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Use </seg>2</label> of this point may be a good an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidote against Pride in a prosperous Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,<note place="margin">Nemo confidat nimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um secundis, rotat o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mne fatum, <hi>Sen.</hi> Thyest. trag. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note>, since God hath so ordered the Web of our lives, as that Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versity as well as Prosperity is interwo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in it: For there is nothing that swels us up so much as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spering here in world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things;<note place="margin">Hen caecae mentes tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mefactaque corda se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundis. <hi>Silius 1.</hi>
               </note> and nothing again that is more effectuall to asswage this swelling in us, then to consider the brevity and mutability it is subject to.</p>
            <p>Now it swells us up with a high opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on either of our own Goodnesse above o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, or else of our own Greatnesse.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Our prospering in worldly things
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:34421:36"/> swels us up with a high opinion of our own Goodnesse above others; as</p>
            <p n="1">1. It makes us think our selves the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly good men in Gods eye, because we are prosperous in the worlds; whereas in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, this can be no certain rule to mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure out any such thing by, since the world and the prosperity of it is so variable and uncertain.</p>
            <p>And therefore, when at any time God shall water us more then others with the lower springs of his earthly Blessings, we are not therefore to have an overweening conceit of our selves, and our own causes, above others, (as if God upon this ground had tyed his speciall love either to us, or them:) For you know that when God would chuse a King for <hi>Israel,</hi> he chose him not by outward and perishing excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies,<note place="margin">1 Sam. c. 16. vers. 8.9. and 10.</note> for then he would have chosen in the room of <hi>Saul, Eliab, Aminadab,</hi> or <hi>Shammah,</hi> who were the three elder bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of <hi>David,</hi> and men of goodly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonages to look upon; yet God chose none of these, (sayes the Text) but <hi>David</hi> the youngest of them, though not so outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:34421:36"/> yet inwardly glorious, being a man af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his own heart?</p>
            <p>It is the chief argument the <hi>Turks</hi> use at this day, to prove themselves the only <hi>Musselmen,</hi> or true believers; We thrive (say they) and prosper in the world; for how hath our <hi>Mahometanisme</hi> over-run all <hi>Asia, Africk,</hi> and the greater part of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope</hi> too! And do not they among us then reason more like <hi>Turks</hi> then <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians,</hi> who speak after this manner, Come, see how we bear down all before us, and ride upon the backs of the poor in triumph! Thus, and thus do we prosper in the world, and do even what we list; and is not this an evident signe we are Gods children, and that the right end of the staff is ours? Sure, if we were other then Gods peculiar people, he would not blesse us so much as he doth.</p>
            <p>But to these I answer, That these and such like are only <hi>Bona Scabelli,</hi> (as Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines distinguish well out of that place of <hi>Isaiah,</hi>) and not <hi>Bona Throni,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Isa. 66.1.</note> the goods of Gods Footstool, (but earthen ware,)
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:34421:37"/> and not the good things of his Throne, which are Grace and Glory; and therefore can set upon us only an earthly mark for men here to take notice of us, but not any heavenly cognizance for God to look upon us, as upon his dear and elect children. For else it would easily follow, That the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choran</hi> were better then the <hi>Bible,</hi> and the <hi>Turks</hi> fancy better then our Faith of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stianity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And were there no other signall place of Scripture for this, then that of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>David</hi> in his 73.<note place="margin">Consule <hi>Ecclesiastes 7.</hi> vers. <hi>15.</hi> See <hi>Ecclesia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes</hi> chap. <hi>8.</hi> vers. <hi>14. Malachy 3.</hi> vers. <hi>13.</hi> and <hi>15. Luke 16.25.</hi> Remember how thou in thy life receivedst thy good things, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Psalm,</hi> (as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed there are very many;) this alone (methinks) were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to impresse this as a truth upon us, where he speaks of some that are not in trouble like other men, but pride compas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth them about as a chain, violence co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers them as a garment, their eyes stand out with fatnesse, and they have more then their heart can wish; yet these
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:34421:37"/> (sayes he) vers. 12. are the ungodly who prosper in the world. And the Prophet <hi>Jeremy</hi> makes bold to question with God about it, in these words, <hi>Jer.</hi> 12.1. and 2. verses: <hi>Wherefore,</hi> sayes he, <hi>doth the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked prosper? and why are all they in wealth that rebelliously transgresse?</hi> and he rests satisfied with this, vers. 3. That God did by that prosperity of theirs fatten them as sheep to the slaughter, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare them for the day of destruction. And this is that prosperity of fools that the Wise man speaks of, which will destroy them. <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.32.</p>
            <p>It is not then our thriving in Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralls, but in Spiritualls, that speaks us and our Faith to be accepted of God.</p>
            <p>For the truth of Grace or Religion, and the goodnesse of a mans cause, is not mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured by the Souldiers Sword, but by the Word of God, which is the Sword of the Spirit.</p>
            <p>God Saints no man for his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly personage,<note place="margin">Ethnicus Deum sic loquen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem inducit: Isti quos pro felicibus aspicitis, si non qua occurrunt, sed qua la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent videritis, vere sunt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seri; Intus enim omne posui bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um. <hi>Sen. lib. de Provid. cap. 6.</hi>
               </note> for his riches, for his
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:34421:38"/> politick head-piece of contriving, and bringing about his own worldly and sinister ends, or for his armes and conquests; for then <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Craesus, Ahitophel</hi> and <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great had been high in Gods book: but he va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lues men only by their spirituals, as their graces of Faith, Humility, Patience, Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, Obedience, and the like: and where he finds these, (how unfurnished soever they are otherwise,) yet <hi>these are mine saith the Lord;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Malachy 3.17.18.</note>
               <hi>and in that day when I shall make up my Jewels, I will spare them, even as a Father doth his Sonne; and then shall ye discern between the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous and the wicked, betwixt him that feareth God, and him that feareth him not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Indeed God may sometimes, permit e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill to prosper in the world, but never ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of it: for so acknowledges the <hi>Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ish</hi> Church, <hi>Lament.</hi> 3.35. <hi>To turn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side the right of a man before the face of the most High,</hi> or <hi>to subvert a man in
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:34421:38"/> his cause, the Lord approves it not.</hi> And therefore to argue from Gods permission to his approbation,<note place="margin">Psal. 55.3.</note> is a grosse <hi>Non sequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi> nay more, a laying our iniquity on Gods back, as if he would take it well at our hands to be made a Pack-horse at every turn to bear all our execrable bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens,<note place="margin">Psal. 50.21.</note> and were (as <hi>David</hi> speaks) such a one as our selves, to favour evil cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, or else to own them as his off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spring.</p>
            <p>Which made <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nysius</hi> the elder con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude Sacriledge to be no sinne,<note place="margin">Videtis (inquit) quam prospera navigatio à Diis immortalibus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur Sacrilegis. <hi>Valer. Max.</hi> lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> when he had rob'd the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple at <hi>Locri,</hi> because the Gods seem'd (as it were) to smile up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the action, in giving them fair Winds and Weather, both in their voiage thither and return back again.</p>
            <p>But, as it was a great blasphemy (sayes one) for the Devill to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonate God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sr</hi> Franc. Bacon <hi>Es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>say</hi> 3.</note> when he
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:34421:39"/> would be <hi>similis Altissimo;</hi> so is it greater to make God personate the Devil. And yet this he doth, that makes God patronize his evil,<note place="margin">Prosperum scelus vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus vocatur. <hi>Sen.</hi> trag. in <hi>Herc.</hi> fur.</note> because he prospers in it; for this brings in God saying, That he will be like the Prince of Darknesse, and makes the Holy Ghost to leave his Dove-like shape, and come only to us in the form of a greedy Raven or Vultur.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As our prospering in worldly things swells us up too high with an opinion of our own Goodnesse, and makes us think better of our selves then is meet; so also doth it on the other side lift us up too farre with thoughts of evil towards our brethren, and make us think worse of them, and the wayes of God they walk in, then we should, by char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging them as utterly deserted of God,<note place="margin">Adversae res etiam bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos detrectant. <hi>Salust.</hi>
               </note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause we see not now the same hedge of Gods favour about them as heretofore we
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:34421:39"/> did, but the stakes that then prop'd them up, are now thrown away as uselesse and unserviceable. Whereas Afflictions on this hand are every way as temporary and transient, as Prosperity was on the other; and being so, must needs be as a broken reed, or a reed of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> wherewith we cannot exactly measure Gods Temple, nor the spirituall estate of his Children.</p>
            <p>It was a hard stumbling-block to the Prophet <hi>David</hi> for a time,<note place="margin">Psal. 73. ver. 2.</note> when he sayes that his <hi>feet were almost gone, and his foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steps had well-nigh slipt,</hi> upon his sight of the wickeds prosperity; untill he went in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Sanctuary of Gods Word, where he learnt to settle his wavering and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trustfull thoughts: for there he saw that notwithstanding his outward afflictions, that God held him up under that sore temptation with his right hand,<note place="margin">ver. 23.</note> and would (in opposition to transitory goods, which are the proper blessings of the wicked, because they have no others but these to trust unto) guide him with that which should infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely exceed them, to wit, his Counsell here, and his Glory hereafter.</p>
            <p>And it was the great question so much
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:34421:40"/> agitated betwixt <hi>Job</hi> and his Friends, Whether those dolefull changes that befell him were the cognizance of his insincerity to God, and of Gods disfavour to him upon it, yea or no. His Friends taking ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage upon his present weaknesse and distemper, maintain it strongly against him in the affirmative, that they were: untill at length God himself steps in to the rescue of the weaker side, and makes the conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion (as all logicall conclusions do) to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the weaker part,<note place="margin">Conclusio sequitur de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biliorem partem. <hi>Kick.</hi> log. pag. <hi>424.</hi>
               </note> determining it for <hi>Job</hi> against his Opponents in the negative, and telling them, that they spake not of <hi>Job,</hi> nor of his proceedings towards him that which was right. <hi>Job</hi> last. vers. 7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seneca</hi> a <hi>Stoick</hi> Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losopher hath a set discourse to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose,<note place="margin">In libro de provid. cap. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Cur bonis viris mala eveniant,</hi> why the evils of this life most commonly fall out to good men: and he concludes it thus, That temporall
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:34421:40"/> evils are no sign of Gods hatred to them.<note place="margin">Numquid tu invisot esse <hi>Lacedemoniis</hi> suos liberos credit, querum experiuntur indolem publice verberibus ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motis? Non est hoc saevitia; certamen est.</note> For, dost thou think (sayes he) that the <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> hated their Children, when as they experimented their disposition to vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue by stripes in publick? No, So do we think Gods children in disfavour with him, because he layes here sore blows upon their bodies and estates by evil men,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>So</hi> Tametlain <hi>the</hi> Scy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thian <hi>was call'd</hi> Fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gellum Dei.</note> as his rods and scourges in it? No; for we see and feel many times (sayes an experimentall patient of our own well) the deep lines and strokes of Gods hand upon us,<note place="margin">Sir I. M.</note> when as we cannot by our skill in Palmestry decipher his meaning in it, no more then the <hi>Malteses</hi> could by the viper upon Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> hand judge of his condition to God-ward.<note place="margin">Acts 28.4.</note>
            </p>
            <p>For God sometimes (that we may not thus judge) inverts humane order, and runs out his dealings towards us in the ordinary chanel of his universall provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:34421:41"/> justice and equity, by which he wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters here all alike.</p>
            <p>Indeed they may seem (I grant) to go counter to our apprehended rules of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon right: yet are they alwaies agreeing both with Gods secret and revealed will, though (like the sunne in its sphear) not perceptible to us, because too mysterious and dazzling: however many pretend to interpret them by a blaze of fire lighted at the naturall pride of their own private spirits, and that dimme twilight of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge which is in them; whenas they are altogether in the dark to the true light of Gods word and works herein.</p>
            <p>And here take in the opinion also of <hi>Epictetus</hi> another <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ick</hi> and Heathen man,<note place="margin">Pia <hi>Epicteti</hi> sententia, Non esse omnes Deo ex osos, qui aerumnarum varietate luctantur, sed esse arcanas causas, ad quas pancorū potest per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venire curiositas. <hi>Aus. Gell.</hi> noct. Att. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> which speaks most Christianly to this point, namely, That all are not hated of God, who do wrastle here with variety of Miseries: but that there are with God good
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:34421:41"/> causes of it, though so secret that few can reach them.</p>
            <p>And therefore, albeit we cannot see how these actings of God may stand with his tender love to his children, and so may conceive an ill opinion of them; yet when we shall think seriously,<note place="margin">Isa. 55.8.</note> that Gods thoughts and wayes are not as ours, it will teach us to give them a more favourable inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation.</p>
            <p>For how dare hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane rashnesse (sayes Saint <hi>Bernard</hi>) repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend that which it cannot comprehend;<note place="margin">Quomodo humana teme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas audet reprehendere quod comprehendere non potest! De <hi>Consid.</hi> l. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> in giving demonstra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive reason why world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prosperity should be virtues stepdame,<note place="margin">Noverca virtutis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speritas. <hi>P. Chrysol.</hi> lib. <hi>1.</hi> de curial. nugis.</note> and not her naturall mother!</p>
            <p>But (to close up this discourse) you see here by what hath been said, that it is a great errour (howbeit now grown more then popular) to judge of persons and causes by the events, whenas <hi>all</hi> outward
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:34421:42"/>
               <hi>things</hi> (sayes <hi>Solomon) fall alike to all, neither can any judge of love or hatred by what is before him;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ecclesiast. c. 9. ver. 1.</note>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See also</hi> Mat. <hi>5.45.</hi> He makes his sun rise on the evil and on the good, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> Prosperity and Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sity being but separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble accidents to them, and no essentiall properties of them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they are grounded upon worldly things that have so loose and mouldring a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, as that a man cannot tell con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning them what a day may bring forth Again</p>
            <p n="2">2. As worldly prosperity swels us up with a high opinion of our own Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse above others, so likewise of our own Greatnesse. And this makes us slight those that are under us, and deal hardly with them, (as to temporall things,) which we would not do, if we once consider'd the mutability of it.</p>
            <p>And therefore if at any time God shall give up unto us those we conceit our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, to be dealt with (if we will) by all harshnesse and extremity; yet are not we then to trample upon them in the pride
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:34421:42"/> of our hearts, not to adde more load to that which God hath already laid upon them, but rather to take off from it what we can,<note place="margin">As the virtue of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versity is fortitude: so is temperance and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of prosperity. Sir <hi>Francis Bacon,</hi> Es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>say <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> and to use them with all gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and compassion, with all mildnesse and moderation, as consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering our selves, that we are not here to live alwayes as Gods upon earth, the same yesterday, to day and for ever: but what is the bitter cup of their portion to day, may be ours to morrow.</p>
            <p>It speaks out but a course and ignoble spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,<note place="margin">Faciles motus mens ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerosa capit. <hi>Ovid.</hi> Trist. lib. <hi>3.</hi> eleg. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> to crow and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sult over those that are down. The very Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then thought it so, who had only the glimmering of nature to guide them; much more ought we Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, whom the Apostle exhorts, that our <hi>moderation may be known to all men.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Philipp. 4.5.</note> That as the Apostle will have his <hi>Corinthians</hi> to <hi>use the world with a</hi> tanquam, <hi>as if they used it not;</hi> so must they among us,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.31.</note> that
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:34421:43"/> have wealth, power and authority, to use them, as if they used them not: that so when they shall fail us, (as they will ere long,<note place="margin">The wind goeth towards the South, and turneth about unto the North; it whirleth about con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually, and the wind returnes again (sayes the <hi>Preacher</hi>) accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his circuits. <hi>Ecclesiastes</hi> 1.6.</note> since the wind blows not alwayes out of one and the same favourable quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) we may then be able to say with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, That we never missimployed those ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents of Gods outward favour to us unto the pressure and destruction of our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, but only to their relief and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Vers. 4. 5. and 6.</note>The Prophet <hi>David,</hi> in his tenth <hi>Psalm,</hi> speaks of some, who <hi>through the pride of their countenance do not seek after God, neither is God in all their thoughts.</hi> But <hi>their wayes are alwayes grievous; they puffe at their enemies, and say in their hearts, they shall never be moved, nor be in Adversity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And such were the <hi>Babylonians,</hi> who (besides their barbarous cruelty to the <hi>Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites</hi>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:34421:43"/> under capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity) added this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all,<note place="margin">The School-men say <hi>Irrisio</hi> is <hi>mortale pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum</hi> in the Agent: Sure I am, it is <hi>mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tale supplicium</hi> in the Patient; for <hi>Ego illam anum irridere me ut sinam?</hi> (sayes he in the comedy;) <hi>satius est mihi quovis exitio in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terire.</hi> Terent. <hi>in</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria.</note> that they scoff'd and jeer'd at them in their mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,<note place="margin">Psal. 137.3.</note> with <hi>Sing us now one of the songs of</hi> Sion. So also were the <hi>Edomites</hi> vers. 7. who cryed over <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rusalem</hi> in the day of her visitation, <hi>Rase it, rase it even to the foundations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And were we sure that the sun of our earthly Happinesse would alwayes stand still in this our <hi>Gibeon,</hi> it may be we might take liberty to do the like, and think we did well in it too. But when as we come to consider seriously, that there is no Solstice here upon earth, but so soon as the Sun is come to his furthest Summer-point in our Horizon, it is then presently verticall, and turning again to make Winter-weather with us, how will this asswage that swelling of pride that is within us, and make us humble?</p>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:34421:44"/>
            <p>To this purpose there is a memorable histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of <hi>Caganus</hi> King of the <hi>Huns,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bucholc. <hi>chronol. pag.</hi> 669.</note> unto whom <hi>Theodorus Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicus</hi> being sent in an embassy from <hi>Mauri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> the Emperour, to divert those swarms of people wherewith <hi>Caganus</hi> at that time threatned to storm the Empire, he apply'd himself to him in these words;<note place="margin">Vid. <hi>Herodot.</hi> hist.</note>
               <hi>Audi,</hi> Caga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, <hi>utilem narratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem</hi> Sesostris, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Hear, sayes he to <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganus,</hi> a profitable narrative of <hi>Sesostris</hi> King of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> who being lifted up too high with his great Successes against his enemies, caus'd four Kings taken prisoners to draw his triumphall Chariot, wherein one of them look'd back with smiles to the wheel of the Chariot, and being demanded his reason for it, answered; <q>That he smiled to see the speak of the wheel now at the top, to be presently at the bottome; and again that which is now at the bottome, to be by and by at the top.</q> The very hearing whereof did so mollifie, and keep down the haughty princes spirit, that
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:34421:44"/> it drew him a little to forbear his acts of hostility against the Emperour.</p>
            <p>And from this to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pick also of volubility,<note place="margin">Idem histor. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> did <hi>Craesus</hi> draw an argument to disswade <hi>Cyrus</hi> from his intended inrode into <hi>Scy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thia,</hi> For if thou didst lead (sayes he) an immortall army, then is there no need for thee to ask my advice in it; but if thou dost acknowledge thy self a man, and a leader of mortals, then think that there is a wheel of humane affairs that turns about continually, and suffers nothing here below to stand long upon the same bottom.</p>
            <p>But this advice of <hi>Craesus</hi> took no place with <hi>Cyrus:</hi> If it had, he would have kept himself (as the <hi>Tortoise</hi> doth) <hi>intra testudinem,</hi> within his own shell, within his own dominions, and not have cause<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lessely usurp'd upon the rightfull possessions of others to his own destruction; for see the issue and event of it.</p>
            <p>Even that God who is infinite in his Wisdome, and terrible in his Power and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:34421:45"/> He that resists the proud,<note place="margin">Psal. 138.6.</note> and looks upon them afarre off; He (I say) made the pride of <hi>Cyrus</hi> serve as a snare to take him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self in,<note place="margin">Alios in cladem meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam praecipitavit indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne aucta faelicitas. <hi>Boer.</hi> de Consol. philos. l. <hi>4.</hi> pros. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> and to work his ruine: for he was no sooner entred <hi>Scy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thia,</hi> but he found by sad experience how unconstant the world was, not looking now upon him with that smiling aspect it did before; but the wind was now in another quarter,<note place="margin">Prov. 23.5.</note> and (as the Wise man sayes of Riches, that <hi>they make themselves wings and fly away,</hi>) so did his former prosperity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take her self now to her wings, and flew a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way,<note place="margin">Consule <hi>Justin.</hi> hist. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> his whole army being quite defeated, and himself slain by <hi>Tomyris</hi> Queen of <hi>Scythia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A good example to make the secure wretch-look about him, and to pull down the high looks of the proud.</p>
            <p>And therefore when ever any flushing of pride begins to rise within thee, and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:34421:45"/> to bud forth, as it is in <hi>Ezekiel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 7.10.</note> into vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and oppression of others, then think thou hearest some Monitor calling unto thee, as King <hi>Philip's</hi> Page did to him, <hi>Memento te esse mortalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Q. Curt.</note> remember that thou art mortall: so, remember that thou art changeable as well as others, and this will be an excellent means to keep it in.</p>
            <p>For tell me, would <hi>Cyrus,</hi> think you, have invaded <hi>Scythia,</hi> had he thought so sad a fate would have attended him in it?</p>
            <p>Or would <hi>Pharaoh</hi> have oppress'd the <hi>Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites</hi> so much, had he thought that God would have tumbled him up and down so much as he did, from one plague to another,<note place="margin">Exod. 5. chap.</note> and at last made the sea his champion to revenge their injuries upon him?</p>
            <p>Or would <hi>Joseph's</hi> brethren have perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted him as they did, if they had thought he should afterwards have been lord over them?</p>
            <p>Or the <hi>Gileadites</hi> have expelled <hi>Jephtha,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Judg. chap. 11.</note> had they known he would have been such a shelter against a storm, and of such use unto them against the <hi>Ammonites?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or (to say no more) would <hi>Darius</hi>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:34421:46"/> have call'd <hi>Alexander Philip</hi>'s boy in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rision of him,<note place="margin">Q. Curt.</note> had he known that he should have been conquered by him?</p>
            <p>No; Little do proud men think that the water which is now in the float, will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently be in the ebbe; and that the spoak of the wheel which is now at the top, may quickly be at the bottome: and then he that is the greatest now among us, may come (how soon he knows not) to stand in need of the meanest creature whom he now despises.</p>
            <p>It is wisdome then for every Christian,<note place="margin">Sapienter omnes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trabant vento nimium secundo turgida vela, <hi>Hor.</hi> carm. l. <hi>2.</hi> od. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> whenas he is at the top of the wheel, and may lord it over those that are beneath, yet not to overlook them with a scornfull eye, but to let down his spirit, and (as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle exhorts us) to condescend to men of low degree:<note place="margin">Rom. 12.15.</note> For one scale is not alwayes in depression. No; This were <hi>dura infaelicitas,</hi> a very hard and high measure of infelicity. Neither is the other alwayes in elevation: This were <hi>faelicitas miseranda,</hi> a happinesse
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:34421:46"/> to be pitied. But the alternate wave of the beam keeps them both in aw, and espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the proud person, who seems unto me as a bird tied to a string, which if i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fly too high, the hand draws in the string and puls it down again. And so if we shall let out our spirits too high with pride, God hath then a line of vicissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude in his hand to pull us in at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure.</p>
            <p>The Prophet <hi>David</hi> said in his prosperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that he should never be moved,<note place="margin">Psal. 30.6.</note> his mountain was made so strong; yet God did but hide his face from him a little, and he was troubled.</p>
            <p>Naturally then we are too apt to know no measure in a high fortune;<note place="margin">Res secundae non habent unquam modum. <hi>Sen.</hi> in <hi>OEpid.</hi>
               </note> but (as a person of Honour and Piety in this nation said) Although in the heat of summer we easily believe there will come after it a cold season of frost and snow:<note place="margin">The Lord <hi>C.</hi> in his <hi>74</hi> meditat.</note> yet are we so stupid as in Prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity not to consider of Adversity, though
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:34421:47"/> the one be as successive as the other. And this makes us to exalt our selves so much above all that is called God. That as it is obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable touching the book of <hi>Esther</hi> (which is nothing else but a Declaration of acts done in reference to the Greatnesse, Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Glory of <hi>Ahasuerus</hi> the <hi>Persian</hi> Monarch, as to the principall instrument of them) that in that whole book the name of God is not so much as mentioned at all: So doth it also commonly fall out, that while we are here in the ruffe of our worldly Glory and Prosperity, we seldome or never speak of God, and as seldome think of him, but set our selves up in his room, as <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> did, who spake too big, and too much of himself, saying, <hi>Is not this great Babel that I have built for the house of my Kingdome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 4.30.</note>
               <hi>by the might of my power, and for the honour of my ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty?</hi> As the fly said in the Apologue when it was got up to the top of the wheel,<note place="margin">Quam magnam vim pulveris excitavi! <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sop.</hi> fab. pag. <hi>62.</hi>
               </note> See what a dust I make! So, see what a dust
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:34421:47"/> makes this poor Worm, what a <hi>Mying</hi> there is with him in the height of his pride! nothing but <hi>my</hi> Kingdome, <hi>my</hi> Power, and <hi>my</hi> Majesty: but as for God,<note place="margin">Erasm. Adag. <hi>pag.</hi> 674.</note>
               <hi>Ne gry qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem,</hi> There is not a word of him; He is not in all his thoughts.</p>
            <p>And therefore how soon the house of his Kingdome fell upon his head, yea how short-liv'd the might of his power was, and the honour of his majesty, you may see by the next verse, where it is said, That while the word was in the Kings mouth, there fell a voice from heaven say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>O</hi> Nebuchadnezzar, <hi>to thee be it spoken, Thy Kingdome is departed from thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The world then may well be compared to the sea of glasse which Saint <hi>John</hi> saw in his vision, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velat.</hi> 4.6. and there be also,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leo</hi> his Conc. funeb. in obit. Doctoris <hi>Featlaei.</hi>
               </note> that from the resemblance of the one to the other, interpret it thus. For</p>
            <pb n="86" facs="tcp:34421:48"/>
            <p>First, It resembles the sea either for its ebbing and flowing: or else for the sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain change of it: for how soon is the face of the sea alter'd?<note place="margin">Nunc strato aequore blanditur mare: nunc fluctibus inhorrescit. <hi>Boet.</hi> de Consolat. Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losoph. lib. <hi>2.</hi> pros. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> In one and the same hour (it may be) thou mayest see her smiling upon thy vessel, and frowning too; playing with it, and swal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing it up. <hi>Noli igitur</hi> (sayes the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralist) <hi>tranquillitati e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus credere.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sen.</hi> de tranquill. ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi. Eodem die quo tibi luserant navigia, sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bentur.</note>
               <hi>i. e.</hi> Do not therefore trust too much to her smooth and calm looks; <hi>in hoc enim momento ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re evertitur,</hi> for in one moment doth she appear wrinkled with billowes, and turns about from a calm unto a storm.</p>
            <p>Secondly, In resem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles also glasse,<note place="margin">We say therefore of glass usually, that it stands in harme way; and some melancholy persons have conceited their bodies to be of a glassy substance, and would not let any man touch them for fear of breaking. See <hi>Burton</hi>'s Melancholy.</note> and that either for its brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlenesse, because no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is sooner bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: or else for its
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:34421:48"/> slipperinesse, because he that walks upon glasse can have no sure footing; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for any man to presume upon the stea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinesse of it must needs be very dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous.</p>
            <p>That as the ancient <hi>Romans</hi> used to distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guish their dayes into <hi>Dies albi</hi> and <hi>Dies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tri,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Godwin</hi> Rom. Antiq. lib. <hi>2. §. 3.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi> &amp; <hi>Erasm.</hi> Adag. pag. <hi>105.</hi>
               </note> white and black dayes: so doth God, and there is no man but hath the later of these as well as the former, his black as well as his white dayes.</p>
            <p>Oh the madnesse then of wicked men, who are alwayes plotting against the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, and gnashing upon them with their teeth! <hi>At ridebit Deus,</hi> sayes <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 37.12.</note>
               <hi>But God shall laugh at them</hi> for it: and he gives this reason vers. 13. <hi>because he sees that their day is coming. i. e.</hi> he sees clearly that their black and dismall day is coming upon them, though themselves will
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:34421:49"/> not see it through the pride and security of their spirits; yea, and he knows also punctually when it will be: though we know it not, for though to day may be fair and shining, yet may to morrow be dark and tempestuous with them; Since we know not what a day may bring forth.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Use </seg>3</label> Last of all (because I am loth that my sun should set in a cloud;) The conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of this point may serve as a good an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidote against despair in an afflicted condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;<note place="margin">Nemo desperet meliora lapsus —prohibet <hi>Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho</hi> stare fortunam, <hi>Sen. Thyest.</hi> trag. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> or as a cordiall to stay up our spirits in the saddest and most di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stressed times, and to teach us patience and contentednesse in them: that so as in prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity we should not say, we shall never be moved, so neither in adversity, that we shall never be deliver'd; when we shall consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that what weight of affliction soever we ly under,<note place="margin">Non si male nunc, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lim sic erit. <hi>Horat.</hi> lib. <hi>2.</hi> ode <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> is not of a continuant, but of a changeable nature. And to this end
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:34421:49"/> we have the sure staff of Gods promise unto his children to lean upon, as in the tenth chapter to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> where he sayes thus, <hi>Yet a little while,</hi> or rather as it runs in the <hi>Greek,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.37.</note> yet how very very little while, (with a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble diminutive) <hi>and he that shall come, will eome, and will not tarry.</hi> And in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent verse he tells them, they have need of patience, that they may receive this promise. And in the twelfth chapter to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> the Apostle takes up an exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to it from the Wise man,<note place="margin">Prov. 3.11.</note> and makes a consolatory use of it to his <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews,</hi> withall taking them to taske for their forgetfulnesse of it;<note place="margin">Heb. 12.5.</note>
               <hi>And ye have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten the exhortation which speaks unto you, as unto children: My sonne, despise not thou the chastening of the Lord, nor faint,</hi> or be not broken in mind,<note place="margin">Ne animo frangitor; sic <hi>Beza.</hi>
               </note> (as others translate it) <hi>when thou art rebuked of him.</hi> For <hi>we had</hi> (sayes he) <hi>the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of our flesh, who verily chastened us
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:34421:50"/> a few dayes after their own pleasure,</hi> and <hi>we</hi> were patient under their rod,<note place="margin">See the 9. and 10. ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses.</note> and <hi>gave them reverence, but God</hi> a few dayes only, <hi>for our profit. Shall we not then be much rather in subjection to him who is the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of spirits, and live?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus when <hi>Boetius,</hi> that Christian Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sul and Martyr at <hi>Rome,</hi> was wrongfully deprived by <hi>Theodoricus</hi> of his Honours, Estate and Liberty, Philosophy brings in what we call Gods providence, comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him in these words;</p>
            <p>I turn about my wheel continually,<note place="margin">Rotam meam volubili orbe semper verso, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fimis summa, summis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que infima mutare gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens. Quid igitur a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimo contabescis, <hi>&amp;c. Boet.</hi> de Consol. lib. <hi>2.</hi> pros. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> and delight to tumble things upside down: why then doth thy heart shrink within thee, when as this changeablenesse of mine is cause e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for thee to hope for better things?</p>
            <p>And so also, when many of our brethren were heretofore in exile for their Religion in Queen <hi>Marie's</hi> dayes, what (I pray)
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:34421:50"/> did that <hi>Jewell</hi> of our Church comfort them with, but only this,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>In</hi> Juelli vita.</note>
               <hi>Haec non durabunt, aetatem</hi> These will not endure an Age? as indeed you know they did not, her reign being not full out six years time.</p>
            <p>And with the same consideration also should we cheare up our selves now un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that black cloud that hangs over the Church,<note place="margin">Non semper imbres nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bibus hispidos manant in agros. <hi>Hor.</hi> lib. <hi>2.</hi> ode <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> that it will not endure an Age, but be as <hi>Ephraim's</hi> righteousnesse was,<note place="margin">Hos. 6.4.</note> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven like the morning cloud; or as the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dew that passes away.</p>
            <p>To this end, it will not be amisse to note, how the afflictions of Gods people in the Scripture, are run out not by any long tract of time, as by an Age, Year, Moneth, Week or the like; but by the shortest measures that can be, as by a Day: now a Day (you know) holds not long, but is quickly gone, even as a flying bird, or a poast that runneth by. And this good
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:34421:51"/>
               <hi>Hezekiah</hi> calls the time of <hi>Sennacheribs</hi> rage against <hi>Judah,</hi> a Day of trouble, <hi>Isa.</hi> 37. <hi>vers.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>Or if this be not enough, you have them then contracted within a lesser room, and measur'd only by a Night, which is no more but the dark side of a naturall day, and therefore is a great deal shorter. And this made the Prophet <hi>David</hi> say, <hi>Psal.</hi> 30. vers. 5. That <hi>heavinesse may endure for a night, but joy cometh in the morning.</hi> The time then that heavinesse shall endure to the Godly can be but a Night at the longest, but whether it shall be so long or no, the Prophet is very uncertain and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>satisfied, for which cause he expresses it here with a <hi>May be, Heavinesse may endure for a night.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if this expression be not full enough to set forth the brevity of them, our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour</hi> doth it then by an Hour, which is shorter yet, and but the four and twentieth part of a naturall Day; for so he calls the time of his persecution by the High Priests and Elders of the people, Their <hi>hour,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:34421:51"/> and the power of Darknesse. Luk.</hi> 22.53.</p>
            <p>Or, if this be yet too long a space to set forth the brevity of their afflictions, and to give a through Comfort to Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, their little continuance is then express'd by a Moment, which I am sure is short enough; so you have it <hi>Isa.</hi> 54. vers. 7. <hi>For a small moment</hi> (sayes God to his Church) <hi>have I forsaken thee, but with great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy will I gather thee:</hi> And again vers. 8. <hi>In a little wrath I hid my face from thee for a moment, but with everlasting kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse will I have mercy upon thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or last of all, if any time can be short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then this, it must then be the present time; yet such are the sufferings of Gods children, in Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> account, but <hi>the Sufferings of the present time,</hi> Rom. 8.18. and a shorter time then this there cannot be. For as the <hi>French</hi> our neighbours are said to be for their inconsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deratenesse,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Howell</hi> in the life of <hi>Lewis</hi> the thirteenth.</note>
               <hi>Animalia sine praeterito &amp; futu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro,</hi> Creatures that have respect neither to time past nor time to come: so may we say
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:34421:52"/> of the present time, That it is as short a measure as can possibly be imagined, having in it nothing either of time past or future, the first of the two being dead already, and the later of them being not yet born unto us. And yet we see here for all this that Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> when he had cast up the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of all which he suffered in the cause of Christ, how he reckons and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes it to be only the suffering of the present time, and not worthy to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with the glory that shall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He that observes the wind</hi> (sayes <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon) shall never sow,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ecclesiast. c. 11. v. 4.</note>
               <hi>and he that observes the clouds shall never reap.</hi> Such are our Troubles, such our Afflictions, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they blow strong against us, yet like some high and mighty wind, they will not hold; yea though they fall upon us as thick as hail, yet are they not so fix'd for ever, but a change shall come. which should make us in any temptation to despair and distrust of Gods providence, check and chide our spirits, as the prophet <hi>David</hi> did his with that objurgation, (which
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:34421:52"/> for the remarkablenesse of it is thrice re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated, in the two and fourtieth and three and fourtieth Psalms;<note place="margin">Psal. 42. vers. 5. and 11. Again Psal. 43. last verse.</note>) <hi>Why art thou cast down, O my soul? and why art thou dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieted within me? Still hope in God; for I shall yet praise him, who is the health of my countenance and my God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Scaliger</hi> tells us of one <hi>Palavicine</hi> an <hi>Italian,</hi> and kinsman of his,<note place="margin">In lib. 18. subtil.</note> that had in one night his hair metamorphosed from black to white: And I apply it thus, That al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though now Gods people may <hi>ly,</hi> as the <hi>Israelites</hi> did, <hi>among the pots,</hi> (to use the Prophets words,<note place="margin">Psal. 68. vers. 13.</note>) and be like some Scullion fullied and black'd with the burning coals of Affliction; yet may one day of Gods favour to us work a great alteration with us, and put such a candy of Prosperity upon us, as that we shall be, as it is there vers. 14. even <hi>as white as the snow in</hi> Salmon.</p>
            <p>And therefore, as <hi>Jobs</hi> resolution was,<note place="margin">Job 14. vers. 14.</note>
               <hi>to wait all the dayes of his appointed time, untill his change should come;</hi> so should every good man wait upon God all the dayes that he shall be pleased to lay trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:34421:53"/> upon him, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther immediately by himself,<note place="margin">Accepimus peritura perituri: quid queri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur? Ad hoc institu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti sumus. <hi>Sen.</hi> lib. de provid. c. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> or else me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately by the hands of evil men as his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struments in it; as knowing that it is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed but for a little while, at the most but a <hi>biduum</hi> or a <hi>triduum,</hi> and then a change shall come, and bring him delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For in mount</hi> Sion <hi>and in</hi> Jerusalem <hi>there shall be deliverance,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joel 2.32.</note>
               <hi>as the Lord hath said: neither shall the rod of the ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly alwayes lye upon the back of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 125.3.</note> but <hi>after two dayes he will revive us,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hos. 6.2.</note>
               <hi>and the third day we shall live in his sight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherefore seeing we are compass'd about,</hi> (as the Authour to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> speaks) <hi>with such a cloud of witnesses,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12.1.2. and 3.</note>
               <hi>let us run on with patience the race that is set before us, looking unto</hi> Jesus <hi>the beginner and finisher of our faith, who for the joy that was set before him, endured the crosse and despi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed the shame. Yea let us consider him that
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:34421:53"/> endured such contradictions of sinners, that so we may not be faint and weary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now <hi>Comfort</hi> Jerusalem <hi>(saith my God)</hi> yea comfort her at the very heart,<note place="margin">Isa. 40.1, 2.</note>
               <hi>and tell her that her sinnes are pardoned, and her warfare is accomplished.</hi> For <hi>the Lord knows,</hi> sayes Saint <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.9.</note>
               <hi>how to deliver the godly out of temptation,</hi> and to make a way for them to escape: That <hi>as the sufferings of Christ in them do abound,</hi> so hath God many wayes to make <hi>their consolations abound</hi> also.<note place="margin">2 Cor. 1.5.</note> If the Devil and his Engineers have <hi>Mille nocendi artes,</hi> a thousand wayes to hurt and destroy them, God will either find or make as many wayes to preserve them: whereof some he will have to be more secret and under ground, others again more open and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious to the eyes of the world; as either by restraining the fury and malice of their persecutours, and stopping their mouthes, that they shall not hurt them, as he did the mouthes of the Lions from hurting <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel;</hi> or else by taking them off by his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroying hand of judgement in the full car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reer of their pride, as he did <hi>Pharaoh, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochus,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:34421:54"/> Herod, Agrippa, Julian</hi> the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state, and many such like; or if none of these wayes, yet by ingratiating them, and giving them favour in the sight of their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, as he did the <hi>Israelites</hi> in the eyes of the <hi>Aegyptians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as God knows <hi>how</hi> to deliver the godly, so also <hi>when</hi> to do it; and a great deal sooner it may be then they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, even within the space and turning about of one day: Since none of us know what a day may bring forth.</p>
            <closer>Trin-uni Deo Gloria.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>